<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>VVords to give to the young-man knowledg and discretion, or, The law of kindness in the tongue of a father to his son by Francis Fuller ...</title>
            <author>Fuller, Francis, 1637?-1701.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2389</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7286</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12251590</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12251590</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40634)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 144:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>VVords to give to the young-man knowledg and discretion, or, The law of kindness in the tongue of a father to his son by Francis Fuller ...</title>
                  <author>Fuller, Francis, 1637?-1701.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 202, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.P. for Obed Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Hebrew at head of title.</note>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Example.</term>
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:1"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> VVORDS To give to the <hi>Young-man</hi> KNOWLEDG AND DISCRETION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> The Law of Kindneſs in the Tongue of a Father to his Son.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Francis Fuller,</hi> M. A.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Vox audita perit,</l>
               <l>Litera ſcripta manet.</l>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 13. 1.</bibl> A wiſe Son heareth his Father's Inſtruction.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. P.</hi> for <hi>Obed Smith,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Daventry</hi> in <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thamptonſhire.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:2"/>
            <head>To my SON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Son,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>A Little while ſince we parted with our Dear <hi>Sam,</hi> never to ſee each other more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the glorious Day of the Reſurrection. Thoſe ſmart Expreſſions that frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drop'd from him (beyond any that I ever yet knew of his Age) were no ſmall joy to me while he liv'd, in hope that he might have
<pb facs="tcp:57120:3"/> been eminently uſeful when grown up to Years, and ſhapen'd by Education, and will make him live to me, tho dead, without carrying any of his Aſhes about me (as <hi>Iphicrates</hi> did of his dead Son) to perpetuate his Memory. I hope you will not eaſily forget him who was (as you uſually ſaid) ſo lovely in your Eye, and ſo much beloved by you, much leſs his latter end; (there was that in it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of your remembrance) and leaſt of all your own
<pb facs="tcp:57120:3"/> Death, ſo much confirm'd by his; he came laſt into the World, but is firſt gone out; as of the two Diſciples that ran to the Sepulchre, the youngeſt came there firſt, but the other followed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him.</p>
            <p>I made an Epiſtle De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatory long before he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that contained ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing relating to you both; but ſhould I publiſh it, it might appear as great a miſtake in the exceſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate an Epiſtle to two Sons, when but one is li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,
<pb facs="tcp:57120:4"/> as that of <hi>Apollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> was in the defect, when he ſaluted <hi>Decimus</hi> by the name of <hi>Quintus,</hi> and to my ſelf an act of Cruelty, <hi>Mezentius</hi>-like, thus to tye the Living to the Dead; therefore have reſolved not to do it.</p>
            <p>The time of my Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance in this World can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be long, yours may be longer, but it is beſt not to think ſo; and therefore do all the good you can. Theſe following Directions are given in order to it, and
<pb facs="tcp:57120:4"/> may, if diligently obſerv'd, aſſiſt you in it.</p>
            <p>I would not be as a <hi>Mercury's</hi> Statue, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect only, and not move; nor as the Crab in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that advis'd her young ones to go forward, whilſt ſhe her ſelf went backward; therefore deſire to carry them about me, with <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> his Title things, for my ſelf, and to be a Practicer of what to you I am an Inſtructer; that I may ſay to you, as <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> to his Souldiers, <hi>Look</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57120:5"/> on me, and do likewiſe: <hi>and hope that will reach <note place="margin">Indè paſco, undè paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor, Inde tibi appono undè ego nivo.</note> your Heart that comes from the Heart of</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Bath,
<date>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 8. 1682.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Affectionate Father, Francis Fuller.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:5"/>
            <head>TO
<table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Scroop.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Mary</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Anthony</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Wood.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Joan</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Richard</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Ridley.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Sarah</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Michael</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Pope.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Martha</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>John</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Dudelſtone.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Suſanna</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>John</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Wickham.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Eſther</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>William</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Whitehead.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Mary</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Henry</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Gibbes.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Godfrey</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Vanettern.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Abigail</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Edwards.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Jane</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Samuel</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Tyſon.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Mary</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Alexander</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Dolman.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Suſanna</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Henry</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Lloyd.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Edmund</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="2">Tucker.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mrs. <hi>Margaret</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table> Inhabitants in the City of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and near to it.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:6"/>
            <p>CHildren are Parents in a new Edition, and who but they ſhould endeavour to prevent the <hi>Errata,</hi> and who (under God) better may, being always with them in their Minority, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Power over them.</p>
            <p rend="indent">They are parts of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, therefore ſhould be as much concern'd for their Welfare as for their own.</p>
            <p>They are committed to their care, and they as Truſtees there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oblig'd, not only to reſtore them upon demand, but better than when receiv'd.</p>
            <p>They are begot in their own ſinful likeneſs, and derive that from them which inclines and diſpoſes them to all Evil; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ought to be matter of their Sorrow, that it is ſo, and no leſs of their care (ſo far as they can) to prevent it: Did they behold the filth on their Souls that they bring with them into the World, they would ſee as much cauſe for
<pb facs="tcp:57120:6"/> Sorrow as Joy, and more to mourn over them, while dead in Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than when dead in Nature: a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> would they conſider how far they have been inſtrumental to it, they would ſee as much reaſon to prevent the miſery that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Had they contributed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it, yet the hazard and danger of their periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing being great, as great fear ſhould poſſeſs them, leſt they ſhould periſh, and as great care that they may not.</p>
            <p>The Heathens knew nothing of this; yet many of them made it their firſt and principal care, to provide Inſtructers for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in Principles of Learning, and Rules of Life, wiſely prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nature by their Diſcipline, accompanying their increaſe of Years with a growth of Vertue, that they might become men, and good together: and what a ſhame
<pb facs="tcp:57120:7"/> will it be if the <hi>Pagan</hi> World af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford better Parents and Children than the <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">What at firſt was principally deſign'd for the good of my Children <hi>(viz.</hi> my two Sons born in <hi>Briſtol)</hi> is now dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to you for the uſe of yours; that I judg'd neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as oblig'd by Duty, and this not improper ſince ye are all in a married ſtate, and have Children. It was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated for my Meridian, but will ſerve yours: and that it may, is the ſincere deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Obliged Friend and Servant, F. Fuller.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SOlomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Fools hate Inſtruction;</hi> viz. not natural, but moral Fools, (for, Fools in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Dialect are the Wicked in <hi>David</hi>'s) They, through Impotency, cannot receive it; theſe, through Obſtinacy, will not. To want Inſtruction is a miſery; to reject it, a ſin; to neglect it, is the ſin of Parents; not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, the ſin of Children;
<pb facs="tcp:57120:8"/> they by inſtructing, ſecure themſelves; and no leſs theſe, by harkening to it. Happy thoſe Parents whoſe Hearts are ſo far turned to their Children as to do it; but more happy, whoſe Childrens hearts are ſo far turn'd to God as to receive it. If this ſhall contribute any thing to either, it will then be as much the Joy, as it is now the Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend, F. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57120:8"/>
            <head>
               <hi>WORDS</hi> To give to the Young Man Knowledge and Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
            <p>THERE are three Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in Philoſophy own'd by ſome, <hi>(viz. Matter, Form,</hi> and <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation)</hi> and ſo there are three principal and prime Truths in Divinity to be inquired into, and known by all that expect Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Their Miſery by Nature.</item>
               <item>2. Their Recovery out of it.</item>
               <item>3. Their Duty when Recovered.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. What they are out of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>2. What they are by him.</item>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57120:9"/>
               <item>3. What they muſt do, or how they muſt walk, when in <note place="margin">Col. 1. 27.</note> him.</item>
            </list>
            <p>All which when believed and underſtood, may be as the three <note place="margin">Deut. 4. 41. &amp; 19. 23.</note> Cities of Refuge, for the guilty Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> to flee unto as the three Sons of <hi>Noah</hi> (after <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 18, 19.</note> the Flood) the Seminary of a new World; or (as the three ſtretches of the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> or <note place="margin">1 King. 17. 21, 22.</note> the Widow of <hi>Zarephaths</hi> dear Son) a means to put Life into them, who by Nature are as truly dead Spiritually, as that Child was Naturally.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label>1. Knowledge of Miſery.</label>
            </p>
            <p>Senſe of ſin, and Miſery by i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alone, will do no good, nor any thing without it, for the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Happineſs is laid in it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The knowledge of a Diſeaſe make<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way to a Cure, and ſenſe of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery is the firſt ſtep to Mercy; we uſually ſay, it is moſt miſerable to have been happy, but in this it is the happineſs of ſinners to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57120:9"/> know their miſery, and their greateſt miſery if they do not.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label>2. Knowledge of the way, or means of recovery out of Miſery.</label>
            </p>
            <p>None but Sinners need Mercy, and none but ſenſible ſinners will ſeek for it, but yet they cannot ſeek it aright, unleſs they know the way to it, no more than they can find it, unleſs they ſeek it; the Diſeaſed Woman in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 20, 21, 22.</note> was ſenſible of her Bloody Iſſue before ſhe came to Chriſt, and came to him before ſhe was healed by him; it was not barely the apprehenſion of her Diſeaſe, but the apprehenſion of her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and of Chriſt (her Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian) that cured her: None ſo fit to ſeek for Mercy as humbled ſinners, and none but ſuch will; but yet unleſs they do, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <label>3. Knowledge of Duty, when re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from Miſery.</label>
            </p>
            <p>Converſion is a change from one contrary to another, not from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57120:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> one ſin to another (that is Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie) but from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary one to another; from the privation to the habit, from Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Light, and from Death to Life; this new ſtate calls for a new life, and all that are brought into ſuch a ſtate, muſt live ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to it; they muſt not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2. 12. Eph. 5. 8. 1. Pet. 2. 9.</note> ſinners becauſe they were ſometimes ſo, for once is above any Indulgence granted.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1. Knowledge of Miſery.</head>
                  <p>Senſe of Miſery is neceſſary, not to merit Mercy, but to qualifie for it; not to fit the God of Mercy to give it, but the neceſſitous ſinner to receive it.</p>
                  <p>Now, the miſery of all by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is beſt known (as one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary compar'd with another) by conſidering the happineſs of Man in his ſtate of Innocency.</p>
                  <p>When God had made the World, and richly furniſh'd it with all things for Neceſſity and Delight, he then made Man, not in the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57120:10"/> Image of any inferior Creature, <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 26.</note> but in his own; which Image was both outward and inward, conſiſting partly in his Body, and partly in his Soul.</p>
                  <p>Partly in his Body, As it was <note place="margin">So admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Structure, that <hi>Galen</hi> (a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then) made a Hymn of Praiſe to God that made it.</note> an Inſtrument of Righteouſneſs, and a frame of admirable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure, containing ſo many Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles as Members, ſo many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as parts, and in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree reſembling the Majeſty of God.</p>
                  <p>Partly and chiefly in his Soul, by an inward reſemblance of it to God, not onely in the Spiritual Nature of the Soul, but in the Natural Faculties, Properties, and Endowments of it, <hi>viz. Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>True Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. Knowledge in his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of all that was needful for his ſtate of Perfection and Happineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> A knowledge of God and his Excellencies, of himſelf as to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57120:11"/> Nature of every Faculty of his Soul, and both the temper and uſe of every Member of his Body, and of all other Creatures, both as to Nature and Kind, and how to carry himſelf uprightly to God and them.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Righteouſneſs in his Will.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Natural Inclination (with a power) perfectly diſpos'd to the whole will of God, and to every thing that was juſt, right, and good, without any reluctancy, and of himſelf to will nothing that was not ſo.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. Holineſs in his Affections.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Being free from all Diſorder, Sin, and Impurity, rejoycing in the love and bounty of God, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him as the chiefeſt good in himſelf, and as the Author of all his.</p>
                  <p>As ſoon as <hi>Adam</hi> was made, God planted a Garden in <hi>Eden</hi> (in <note place="margin">Gen 2. 7. 8. &amp; 15, 16, 17.</note> which was every Tree pleaſant to the ſight, and good for Food, the Tree of Life alſo in the midſt of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57120:11"/> the Garden, and the Tree of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Good and Evil) and put him into it to dreſs and keep it, and entred into a Covenant of Life with him (called a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Works) upon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 12.</note> of perfect Obedience, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding him to eat of the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil, upon pain of Death.</p>
                  <p>God might have dealt with him in a way of abſolute Soveraignty, and required Obedience from him without any promiſe of Reward, but he did not, for he entred into a Covenant with him, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Precept, Threatning, and Promiſe.</p>
                  <p>A Precept, requiring perfect and perpetual Obedience.</p>
                  <p>A Threatning, denouncing death if he did not obey it.</p>
                  <p>A Promiſe, aſſuring Life if he did; and though the promiſe is not ſo clearly expreſſed as the threatning, yet as ſtrongly and truly imply'd; for if <hi>Adam</hi> muſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57120:12"/> die if he diſobeyed, he ſhould cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly live, if he did not.</p>
                  <p>The Death threatned was Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, Spiritual, and Eternal; the firſt, in the ſeparation of the Soul <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17. &amp; 3. 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. In dying thou ſhalt dye, and all kinds of Death were threatned.</note> from the Body; the ſecond, in the ſeparation of the Soul from God; the third, in the ſeparation of the Soul and Body from God for ever; one, from the preſence of his Grace here, the other, from that of his Glory hereafter.</p>
                  <p>The Life promiſed imply'd a continuance of his preſent Life, and the aſſurance of one to come; a confirmation of his preſent hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, and a tranſlation (at laſt) to a greater and better.</p>
                  <p>The preſent Life enjoy'd was two-fold; one, as a Man and a Creature; the other, as a perfect and upright Man: The firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in the Union of Soul and Body, the ſecond, in a Union be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and the Soul.</p>
                  <p>The Life to come, was a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, immutable, and eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57120:12"/> both of Soul and Body with God, through a perfect likeneſs to him, and an immediate viſion and fruition of him in Heaven to all Eternity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> being a glorious and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Creature by Creation, and endow'd with a power and will to obey, ſtood bound to obey, both by the Law of Nature, and the <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 14, 15.</note> poſitive Law and Command from God, which obliged him to it.</p>
                  <p>But being made with a freedom of will <hi>(viz.</hi> a liberty of its own accord) to chooſe, or refuſe; to do, or not to do; to ſtand, or fall, at his own choice, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint or force from any; and being mutably good, his will, though naturally diſpos'd to good only, yet being mutable and changeable, it might be altered, and become evil, as it did; for, through the Temptation of the <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 29. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Devil, the perſwaſion of <hi>Eve,</hi> and Pride (a deſire to be as God) through Luxury and Senſuality,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57120:13"/> a diſregard of the promiſe of Life, and a disbelief of Death threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he did eat of the forbidden Fruit, and by it fell from his ſtate of Innocency and Happineſs, into a ſtate of Sin and Miſery.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Of Sin.</hi> In the loſs of his Original Righteouſneſs, and the depravation of his Nature in all <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 5. Job 14. 4. &amp; 15. 14.</note> the faculties of his Soul, and the members of his Body.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Of Miſery.</hi> In the loſs of his Communion with God in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, <note place="margin">Gen. 38. 10. &amp; 23. 1.</note> and ſubjection (as juſtly obnoxious) to all the direful ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and conſequents of his wrath in this World, and in that to come.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> was not a private, but publick Perſon, the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of all Mankind; and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <note place="margin">Acts 17. 26.</note> made with him, was not for himſelf only, but for his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity alſo, that ſhould by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Generation deſcend from him: He was the Head of the Covenant, and they Parties en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57120:13"/> with him by that ſtipula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Legally Parties in that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <note place="margin">Dum puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur aliquis pro peccato primi Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, non punitur pro peccato al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius ſed pro peccato ſuo. <hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas,</hi> quaeſt. 4. de pec. orig. Art. 1. <hi>Rom. 3. 9, 10, 11, 12. &amp; 23. Rom. 5. 18. 19. Rom.</hi> 7. 18<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 19.</note> and as naturally in him (the Head of it) as ſtreams in the Fountain, and branches in the Root; in his ſtanding, they ſtood, and in his fall, they fell; ſinning in him, they fell with him, and partake with him both in his ſin and miſery.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>In his Sin.</hi> By the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that particular ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by him, and by a commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of that corruption deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from him, whereby they are indiſpos'd to all good, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to all evil.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>In his Miſery.</hi> Being juſtly <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 10. Col. 3. 6. Mat. 13. 42. Rom 2. 5. Rev. 19. 20. Mat. 10. 28. Mat. 5. 26. Mark 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 43, 44. 2 Theſ. 1. 9.</note> lyable to all the puniſhments of ſin in this World (both outward and inward) on their Souls and Bodies, and to thoſe in the World to come, in the ſharpneſs, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality, and eternity of them.</p>
                  <p>The Head of <hi>Nilus</hi> is admir'd, becauſe it cannot be found out; but the Spring-head from whence
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57120:14"/> the miſery of all by Nature ariſes, may; <hi>(viz.</hi> from ſin) the Spring is known; but how many, and how bitter the ſtreams are flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from it, cannot eaſily be known; the River that watered the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> branched <note place="margin">Gen 2. 10.</note> out into four ſtreams onely, but the ſtreams flowing from the ſin committed there, are innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; broad and deep, a complex miſery, as to kind and degree, <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 16. &amp; 7. 24.</note> comprehending both ſin and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; ſome are ſins, and not miſeries, and ſome are miſeries, and not ſins; of both which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing may be ſeen in theſe eight following particulars, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Filthineſs.</item>
                     <item>2. Enmity.</item>
                     <item>3. Darkneſs.</item>
                     <item>4. Poverty.</item>
                     <item>5. Nakedneſs.</item>
                     <item>6. Bondage.</item>
                     <item>7. Death.</item>
                     <item>8. Wrath.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57120:14"/>
                     <label>1. Filthineſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt (as he came out <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 5.</note> of Gods hands) was pure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpot or wrinkle, (within and without) but as he came out of <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 45.</note> the Devils hands, or when by ſin that unclean Spirit entred into him, he (and in him all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity) <note place="margin">Iſa. 64. 6.</note> became as an unclean thing.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this <note place="margin">Ezek. 36. 25. Heb. 9. 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. 22. Eph. 5. 26, 27.</note> ſtate, are ſprinkled with the Blood of Chriſt, and cleanſed from all their filthineſs both of Fleſh and Spirit; but they that are not, though Noble by Birth, are but (as <hi>Naaman)</hi> Noble Lepers; tho <note place="margin">2 Kings 5. 1, 2.</note> Princes by Blood, attainted; yea though Angels for outward Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet but as Devils in the ſight of God; in his Eyes they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean, though not in their own, and the more when they are not ſo.</p>
                  <p>Grace is the Ornament of the <note place="margin">Pſal. 16. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 45. 11.</note> Soul, and all that are adorned
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57120:15"/> with it, have Chriſt's Beauty upon them, a Beauty that God greatly deſires, and delights in.</p>
                  <p>But Sin has defiled the whole man, from Head to Foot, not one part only, but every one, inſide and outſide, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A capite ad calcem.</hi> Rom. 6. 19. &amp; 3. 13. Gen. 6. 5. Iſa. 1. 6. 2 Cor. 7. 1. 1 Theſ. 5. 23. Heb. 10. 22. Tit. 1. 15. Eph. 4. 29.</note> Fleſh and Spirit, Body and Soul (the Faculties of one, and Members of the other) Mind and Conſcience, Thoughts and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, Affections and Deſires, Words and Deeds: All of them in general and eſpecial are become altogether filthy by it.</p>
                  <p>Some ſins defile the Body, but all Sins defile the Soul, and that with a filthineſs ſo great, that all the filth in the World (ſhould it meet in one common ſink) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Horrenda vox.</note> equallize the pollution of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Enmity. viz.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Habitual and actual, inward and outward, in Affection or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Reconciliation offer'd, implies
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57120:15"/> it; for, there can be no Reconcili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation <note place="margin">2 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.20.</note> where there is no Breach, nor any Peace made, before the Enmity is ſubdu'd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was in a ſtate of <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Rom. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Friendſhip with God, God and he were as nearly conjoyn'd as a Creator and Creature could be, without ſin; but ſin made a breach, and ſeparated theſe Friends.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this ſtate, have thrown down their Weapons of Hoſtility, are recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled <note place="margin">Rom. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> to God, and at Peace with him; but they that are not, are (like <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Abſalom)</hi> in open <note place="margin">2 Sam. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 5, 6, 7. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> Hoſtility againſt him; and as <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom</hi> made all the means he could to ſtir up the People in Rebellion againſt <hi>David,</hi> ſo they employ their whole ſtrength of Soul and Body againſt God: They are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to him (both actively and paſſively) Haters of God, and hateful to him; Haters of him, and hated by him, as clearly appears <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57120:16"/> by the terms of Difference on their part, and on Gods.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. On their part who gave the Offence. They are Strangers to God, and unacquainted with him, <note place="margin">Job 21. 21. Eph. 2. 12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3, 19. Eph. 4. 18.</note> they are Foreigners, and aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Life of God, without him, afar off, and at diſtance from him, they know not God, nor <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 3. Job 35. 10. Mal. 2. 17.</note> deſire it, (for he is not in all their thoughts) they acknowledge no wrong (ſay not, <hi>What have we</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 8. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>done)</hi> nor repent of their Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs; they ſeek not after God, <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 11 Joh. 5. 40. Jer. 2. 31. Pſal. 14. 2. Pſal. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3.</note> nor for peace with him, nor are willing to come to him for it; they will not accept of Overtures, Parleys, and tenders of Peace, nor read the Articles of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Covenant of Peace, but <note place="margin">Hoſ. 8. 12.</note> count it a ſtrange thing; they will not hearken to God's Voice, <note place="margin">Jer. 13. <hi>ult.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 22. 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 25. 4. Mat. 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. Pſal. 81. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. Pſal. 2. 2.</note> nor regard it, will not be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, nor gathered to him, but reject and contemn him, and take Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt him. They bid him
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57120:16"/> ſtand off and depart (they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ire <note place="margin">Job 21. 14.</note> not the knowledge of his ways) abuſe his Ambaſſadors <note place="margin">Acts 26. 18. 2 Tim. 2. 26. Pſal. 139. 21. Job. 8. 44.</note> that are ſent to treat of Peace, and Liſt themſelves under the Command of Gods utter Enemy the Devil) and riſe up in Arms <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd open Rebellion againſt him.</p>
                  <p>When God is for Peace, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re for War.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. On Gods part.</p>
                  <p>Who as he is a juſt Enemy, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver an Enemy to all impenitent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inners: He is ſtrange to them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eeps at a diſtance, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>raws from them, knows them afar off, and is An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <note place="margin">Iſa. 57. 17. Pſ. 138. 6. Pſal. 7. 11. Pſ. 18. 26. Iſa. 1. 11. &amp; 59. 2. Pſal. 5. 5. &amp; 11. 5. Pſal. 146. 9. Pſal. 1. <hi>ult.</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 19. Prov. 15. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> with them, Curſes their Bleſſings, rejects their Services, and counts them an Abomination, hates them, and walks contrary to them, has a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie with them, Proclaims his <note place="margin">Hoſ. 5. 6. Jer. 25. 31. 1 Pet. 5. 5.</note> Diſpleaſure againſt them, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſts them in open Battel array,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57120:17"/> turns their way upſide-down, and cauſes it to periſh.</p>
                  <p>They are Outlaw'd Enemies.</p>
                  <p>God had no Friends (among Men) untill he made Friends out of Enemies: He was in Chriſt reconciling the World unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. Darkneſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was made a Son of Light (the Candle of the <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 27. <hi>Monſtrum ingens cui lumen ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptum.</hi> Eph. 4. 18.</note> Lord was put into him) but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting the Tree of Knowledge above that of Life, he brought Darkneſs upon himſelf and all his Poſterity.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this ſtate, are Light in the Lord (they <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8.</note> were blind, but now they ſee) <note place="margin">John 9. 25.</note> but they that are not, are Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs <note place="margin">Rev. 16. 10.</note> in the Devil, the Prince of Darkneſs (whoſe Kingdom is full of Darkneſs) they are not onely dim of ſight, but ſtark blind; Children of Darkneſs, doing the works of Darkneſs, which lead to Eternal Darkneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57120:17"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label>4. Poverty.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was the Rich Heir <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 17.</note> of the World, and Lord poſſeſſor of all; but by ſin he became a Bankrupt, and then Juſtice ſeized on him (as the Creditor on his Debtor) and turn'd him the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt <note place="margin">Minimè natus, at maximè dilectus.</note> Poſſeſſor out of all; he was not the firſt-born, yet had a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Portion; but by loſing all at one caſt, he fell into decay, and became the firſt-born of the Poor: <note place="margin">Iſa. 14. 30.</note> He was undone, and all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity had been ruin'd with him, had not Chriſt, the Jewel of the Imperial Crown, been parted with to diſcharge the Debt.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 18.</note> ſtate, are Rich, and have all things; but they that are not, are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Beggars (without ſubſtance <note place="margin">Iſa. 40. 20.</note> or true Riches) having no Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to offer unto God, nor any thing of their own to ſatisfie that double Debt which they owe, <hi>viz.</hi> of Obedience, as Creatures; and of Satisfaction, as Sinners.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57120:18"/>
                  <p n="5">
                     <label>5. Nakedneſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was arrayed with <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 7. Rev. 3. 17.</note> the reſplendent Robe of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, he wanted neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal nor internal Ornaments; but ſin (the Mother of ſhame) defiled them both, and the Devil (as a Conquerour with his Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in War) ſtript him of all thoſe Ornaments, and left him naked.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this ſtate, are clothed with the Robes of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, <hi>(Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in all his Glory was not arrayed</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>like one of theſe)</hi> but they that are not, are in the Raggs of Nature (filthy Raggs) which as filthy, defile, and as Raggs, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hide nor cover the ſhame of <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 18.</note> their Nakedneſs.</p>
                  <p>Sin left us, and Chriſt found us (as the Man in the Goſpel) Naked, and out of our Wits.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57120:18"/>
                  <p n="6">
                     <label>6. Bondage.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt had perfect free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <note place="margin">Acts 8. 23.</note> and was in bondage to none, but Sin brought him, and all his <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 4.</note> Poſterity into it; a Yoak, that neither he their Father was, nor they his Children are, able to bear.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this ſtate, are made Free by Chriſt, <note place="margin">John 12. 31.</note> (the Devil is caſt out, and Rules not as a King, though ſometimes he may as a Tyrant) but they that are not, are Slaves; not onely near to Slavery, but actually in it; they may ſay (with the <hi>Jews)</hi> that they were never in Bondage to any, but they are, and that in Soul and Body too.</p>
                  <p>The Moraliſt ſays, if the great ones of the World were diveſted of their Robes, it would plainly appear what Slaves they were; but all, both great and ſmall, high and low, with all their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Ornaments are Slaves; they were ſo, before they came out of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57120:19"/> the Priſon of the Womb, and greater when out of it than when there, to Sin, and the Devil.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. To Sin.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not onely Pride, but every ſin elſe as a Chain compaſſes them <note place="margin">Pſal. 73. 6.</note> about; for they are in the Bond of Iniquity, ſold under it, and Bond-ſervants to it.</p>
                  <p>So many Luſts, ſo many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and every one give contrary Commands.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. To the Devil.</label> 
                     <note place="margin">John 14. 30. Acts 26. 18. Eph. 2. 2. 2 Cor. 4. 4. 2 Tim 2. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>He is the ſtrong Man, and Prince of this World, that has Snares by which he takes them Captive, and a Power, by which he Rules over them, as a Tyrant over his Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals (from whom he exacts Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute) as a Maſter over his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants (who are under his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand) as a Conquerour over his Captives (who are led by him at his will) and as a Father over his Children (from whom he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects Obedience) they are not onely Children of the Devil, but <note place="margin">1 John 3. 10.</note> Slaves to him.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57120:19"/>
                  <p>They are his by poſſeſſion, though Gods by right.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <label>7. Death.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> at firſt was alive, but when the Devil, the firſt-born of Death (as Prince of Death, and firſt Condemn'd to it) devour'd <note place="margin">Job 18. 13. &amp; 38. 17.</note> his ſtrength, the Gates of Death <hi>(viz.</hi> preſent and certain Death) Temporal on his Body, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual on his Soul, were opened to him; and but a ſtep there was <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 12.</note> betwixt him and Eternal Death.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this <note place="margin">Gal. 2. 20. Eph. 2. 1. Rom. 6. 11. Ma. 8. 22. Rom. 7. 9. Rev. 3. 1.</note> ſtate, are alive in Chriſt, alive by him, and alive to him; but they that are not, are dead, not onely ſick, weak, or diſeaſed, but dead: They may be indeed alive as to their own Opinion, (ſo <hi>Paul</hi> for a time was) and in the Opinion of others (ſo the Church of <hi>Sardis</hi> was) and may be alive as to ſinful works (living in them, and to them) but this their Life is their Death; for it is not a Phyſical Death, which is a loſs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57120:20"/> of the Faculties, but a Moral one, which is a loſs of the goodneſs of them.</p>
                  <p>Sin caſt <hi>Adam</hi> and all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, not into a ſwoon onely, but a Death; and they are all ever ſince by Nature not (as Chriſt ſaid of <hi>Lazarus)</hi> aſleep, but dead <note place="margin">John 11. 11. Luke 10. 30.</note> in ſin; not (as the Wounded Man in the way to <hi>Jericho)</hi> half dead, but altogether ſo, under the ſentence of a Natural Death, under the power of a Spiritual Death, and under the guilt of an Eternal Death.</p>
                  <p>Sons of Death, for they are all <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sententiâ legis.</hi> Pſal. 102. 20.</note> Condemned.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <label>8. Wrath.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>God is Love, and <hi>Adam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency <note place="margin">1 John 4. 8. <hi>Quoad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum non quoad af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum.</hi>
                     </note> found favour in his ſight, and was greatly beloved by him; but by ſin, his Anger was kindled, and his wrath waxed hot againſt him.</p>
                  <p>All that are brought out of this <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1. 10.</note> ſtate, are delivered from wrath (wrath preſent and to come)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57120:20"/> but they that are not, are under wrath, wrath is their Fee-ſimple, and proper Inheritance, to them it is due, and to them it belongs, for as Children of wrath they are <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 3.</note> born to it.</p>
                  <p>The Scripture concludes all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">Rom 3. 23. Eph. 5. 6. Rom. 6. 23.</note> ſin, and ſin concludes all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wrath; it is ſins wages, and God will ſee Juſtice done.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2. Of Recovery out of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery.</head>
                  <p>God left not miſerable Man thus <note place="margin">Luke 10. 30, 31, 32, 33.</note> fallen (as the Prieſt and <hi>Levite</hi> the wounded man in his way to <hi>Jericho)</hi> but (with the good <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan)</hi> had Compaſſion upon him, and ſent his Son to heal thoſe wounds ſin had made, and to recover him from that ſtate of <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 2.</note> Miſery, into which by ſin he was fallen; by his wounds he healed him, and by dying, reſtored him to Life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> was the firſt man, the <note place="margin">Primus foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratus.</note> Natural Head of all men; Chriſt, the ſecond man, the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57120:21"/> Head of all Believers: He was the Earthly man, this the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 47.</note> Lord from Heaven.</p>
                  <p>The Titles given to him, ſhow (as Remedies do the Diſeaſe) the miſery of all by ſin on our part, and the happineſs of all Believers on his.</p>
                  <p>He is a Mediator (and the onely Mediator) an Advocate, a <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 15. &amp; 12. 24. 1 Tim. 2. 5. 1 Joh. 2. 1. Joh. 4. 42. Rom. 11. 26. Heb. 1. 3. 2 Cor. 5. 19. John 1. 12.</note> Deliverer, Healer, and Purger of Sins, a Reconciler, Saviour, and Redeemer; he is all theſe in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and whatever the neceſſities of loſt and undone ſinners can need, or require; but none of them to any, unleſs by Faith they receive him; and therefore, if you expect any help from him, you muſt by Faith go unto him, and you need not fear going, if you <note place="margin">Mark 10. 49.</note> ſee a preſent and abſolute need of him (for, behold he calls you) and this need you will find, if you conſider, that your condition by Nature is no leſs than a ſtate of Filthineſs, Enmity, Nakedneſs,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57120:21"/> Darkneſs, Poverty, Bondage, Death, and Wrath.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. Filthineſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. A Filthineſs ſo deep, that it is not onely extenſive, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſive, <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 22. &amp; 17. 1. Iſa. 1. 18. Jer. 13. 23.</note> compared to marks and brands in the Fleſh (which are not eaſily got out) to colours of the deepeſt dye (double dipt in the wool and web) to the ſpots of a Leopard, (which are not by way of accidental, or exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, but innate coherence) and to the blackneſs of an <hi>Ethiopian,</hi> which cannot be waſht off; the Colliers blackneſs may be waſht off, but not the <hi>Ethiopians;</hi> and the Lepers ſpots may be taken out, but not the Leopards.</p>
                  <p>A Filthineſs ſo great, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Tears of Repentance, nor the Flames of Hell-fire, nor any thing but the Blood of Chriſt, can waſh, or purge it away; the ſacred Laver, cleanſing <hi>Jordan,</hi> and healing <hi>Betheſda,</hi> ſet open for all that will, to waſh in for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57120:22"/> ſin, and uncleanneſs: The Prieſts <note place="margin">Zech. 13. 1. Rev. 1. 5.</note> under the Law, cleanſed by the Blood of Beaſts, but Chriſt by <note place="margin">1 John 1. 7.</note> his own Blood; his will is, that you ſhould be clean, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt by Faith apply his Blood, that you may be ſo.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt waſht his Diſciples Feet with Water, but their Hearts with his Blood, and unleſs he thus waſh you, you can have no part in him; and unleſs by Faith you go unto him, you cannot be thus <note place="margin">John 13. 8.</note> waſhed by him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Enmity.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>A degeneracy beneath the brute Beaſts, for none of them are at enmity with God, with us they are, and we may blame our ſelves for it, for they never Rebell'd, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we Rebell'd.</p>
                  <p>But yet God is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <note place="margin">Iſa. 27. 5. By doubling of the Phraſe, <hi>Make Peace, Make Peace,</hi> as by doubling of the Dream to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> it appears a thing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and eſtabliſht by him, <hi>Cen</hi> 41. 32.</note> to be at peace, for he commands it, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a way to it, and aſſures it to all that like the terms of it, he offers
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57120:22"/> it freely, and ſues for it earneſtly, and therefore it highly concerns you to make peace with him; it is not convenient onely, and fit to be done, but neceſſary, and that which muſt be, and if ever, it muſt be in his way, and at his time.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In his way, <hi>viz.</hi> by Faith in Chriſt, for the bleſſing of peace is the bleſſing of Faith in him, who as Prieſt purchaſed it, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet preached it, and as King works it, in all that believe in him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. At his time, and that is the preſent time, <hi>viz.</hi> of Life, and therefore let not the Sun of your <note place="margin">Luke 12. 58, 59.</note> Life go down upon your Enmity to God, for if you do, terms of peace ſhall neither be offered to you, nor accepted from you.</p>
                  <p>There is no Quarter given in Hell to Enemies.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. Darkneſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Darkneſs that implies a ſtate of evil, both ſinful and penal;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:57120:23"/> not of the Body, but Mind, a <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 18.</note> Corruption of the moſt excellent Faculty, yet not incurable; for, Chriſt the Sun of Righteouſneſs, <note place="margin">Mal. 4. 2. Iſa. 42. 6. Luke 1. 78. 79. Luke 2. 32.</note> the day-ſpring from on High, was ſent into the World as a Light (not onely to all the Types, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies, and dark ſhadows, but) to them that ſate in the darkneſs <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 12. &amp; 12. 46. Acts 26. 18.</note> of ſin and miſery, that from him they might receive the light of Spiritual knowledge and comfort; and therefore, if you are brought out of this ſtate of darkneſs, it concerns you (as the blind Man in the Goſpel did when healed by <note place="margin">John 9. 25, 27, 30.</note> Chriſt) to appear for him againſt all that oppoſe him, to caſt off the works of darkneſs, and walk <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 8.</note> as a Child of light; but if you are not, it concerns you as much, <note place="margin">Mark 10. 46.</note> to go unto him (as blind <hi>Barti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus</hi> did for the Eyes of his Body) <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Omnia ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Chriſtum tenebricoſa,</hi> Marlorat. Luke 4. 18. Rev. 3. 18.</note> that you may receive your ſight. Chriſt is the great Oculiſt ſent from Heaven, and none but he has the Eye-ſalve to cure you.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57120:23"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label>4. Poverty.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>So great is the Poverty you are fallen under by ſin, and ſo low are you brought by it, that all the Creatures on Earth are not able, no, nor all the Angels in Heaven, to raiſe you, or ſet you up again; nothing leſs than the Riches of Heaven, and Treaſures of a Deity can, and Chriſt onely has them, who became poor for our ſakes, that we through his poverty might be rich, and therefore to <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 9. Rev. 3. 18.</note> him you muſt go, that you may be enriched by him: Of other Riches, the promiſe is conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal onely, but of theſe, it is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, but then you muſt come and buy them, and you need not <note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 1.</note> fear, for it is a buying without Money, all the price is a will to accept them.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <label>5. Nakedneſs.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tamar,</hi> when deflowred, rent <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13 18, 19.</note> her Virgin Robe, and ſin by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filing the Soul, rent off the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Garment, that Virgin Robe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57120:24"/> of Innocency, with which it was cloath'd; but Chriſt is not onely Armour for defence againſt weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, an Ornament for Beauty againſt Deformity, but a Veſture for covering, againſt Nakedneſs; and therefore you muſt by Faith put him on, if you would be cloathed with Salvation, not for <note place="margin">Rom. 13. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> an out-ſide Garment of Profeſſion onely, or in ſhew, but in reality; not as a covering for ſin, but for Righteouſneſs in Juſtification, and for Holineſs in Sanctification, as a defence againſt the guilt and power of it, that your nakedneſs may not be uncovered, nor your ſhame ſeen.</p>
                  <p>Your own Righteouſneſs (like the curtail'd Clothes of <hi>David</hi>'s <note place="margin">2 Sam. 10. 4, 5.</note> Ambaſſadors ſent to Comfort <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nun)</hi> is imperfect, ſcanty, and too ſhort to do it, Chriſt's Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs onely can, and without it you can never obtain the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing; <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 15, 27.</note> for, as you came Spiritually naked into the World, ſo if you
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57120:24"/> go out ſo, you will be covered <note place="margin">Dan. 12. 2.</note> with everlaſting ſhame.</p>
                  <p>Onely this you muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that though Chriſts Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs is a Garment large enough to cover you, yet the Rags of Nature muſt be pull'd off before that Robe will come on, for it will come upon none but a naked Soul.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <label>6. Bondage.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>A cruel Bondage, worſe than that of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> for it is to (Sin and the Devil) the worſt of Tyrants, and without the leaſt degree of Eaſe, or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
                  <p>He (in the Goſpel) that was <note place="margin">Mark 5. 3, 4. Luke 4. 13.</note> poſſeſſed, could break all Chains aſunder, but thoſe of the Devil; and from other Bondage you may be able to redeem your ſelf, but from this you cannot, either by your ſelf or others, but by Chriſt onely, the Angel of Redemption, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 18, 19.</note> and great Redeemer, that paid the price of your Ranſom.</p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57120:25"/>
                  <p>You are not free-born, but made ſo, and by none but by him; <note place="margin">John 8. 36.</note> and therefore you muſt by Faith go unto him that you may be ſo; if he make you free, you ſhall be free indeed; but unleſs he do, you muſt be a Slave for ever: Other Slaves, after their Service have Freedom, or by Death obtain it, but they that die in this, are ſo for ever; their Chains are <note place="margin">Jude 6.</note> everlaſting.</p>
                  <p>You muſt be either a King to <note place="margin">Rev. 5. 10.</note> God, or Slave to the Devil.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <label>7. Death.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sin's ſickneſs was to Death, but Chriſt the Heavenly Phyſician, came down to raiſe the dead in ſin to life again; you were kill'd in the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> and may be made alive in the ſecond, but not untill by Faith you receive him; for, <hi>he that hath not the Son of God, hath</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 John 5. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>not life:</hi> It is the life of Heaven in you, that will bring you to that Heavenly Life; and therefore, without this Life of Grace, you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57120:25"/> can have no ſure hope of the Life of Glory, the Title to that, is by Chriſt, and the Title to Chriſt, is by this; ſo that unleſs here you are Spiritually alive by him, you <note place="margin">John 3. 3.</note> cannot hereafter live with him.</p>
                  <p>All that dye in ſin, are buried in Hell.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <label>8. Wrath.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not the wrath of Men, (no, not of the greateſt of them) nor of Devils, but of God; a wrath that cannot be withſtood, for it <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 11.</note> is irreſiſtible, nor endured, for it is intolerable (it cannot be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, much leſs endur'd) nor either avoided, or appeaſed, but by Chriſt, who came to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver from it, and to be as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1. 10. &amp; 5. 9. Cant. 2. 3.</note> from the ſcorching heat of it.</p>
                  <p>There is no way to Mercy, but by deliverance from wrath, nor any way to that, but by laying hold on Mercy, nor any way to <note place="margin">Quarendus eſt Deus, in Pradica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis.</note> Mercy, but by Chriſt, for God is the Father of Mercy, as he is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57120:26"/> the Father of Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <note place="margin">Luke 3. 7.</note> if you would flee from this wrath, you muſt flee to Chriſt, who appeas'd it, and brank that bitter Cup off to the bottom, that you might never taſte of it. <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 39.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nothing but his Blood could quench that flame of wrath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>3. Duty when recovered out of Miſery.</head>
                  <p>All Priviledges (whether Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral or Spiritual, Civil, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious) oblige to Duty, in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they are engagements to it, and ſhould be ſo to all that are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted in them.</p>
                  <p>Spiritual Priviledges are (of all) the higheſt, and moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, they are given to engage to Duty, they afford the beſt means and advantages to it; they aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſin, and become a Curſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Bleſſing, where they are not effectual to it; for, as Mercy abounds, ſo ſin againſt Mercy abounds alſo.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57120:26"/>
                  <p>A change in ſtate calls for a <note place="margin">Nova vita novos mores poſtulat.</note> change in Life, and a new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition requires a new converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>If then you are cleanſed by the Blood of Chriſt from all ſin, keep your ſelf pure and unſpotted from <note place="margin">James 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> ſin and the world.</p>
                  <p>If the Enmity betwixt God and <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 16.</note> you (upon the account of ſin) is ſlain by Chriſt, be ſubject to <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note> his Laws, and live as one recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to him, that all your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 8.</note> may be accepted by him.</p>
                  <p>He that will not accept a gift <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 23, 24.</note> of one at enmity with his Brother, will much leſs accept it from any at enmity with himſelf.</p>
                  <p>If you are called out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs into his marvellous light, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9. Eph. 5. 8.</note> ſhew forth the praiſes of him who has called you out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, by walking as a Child of light.</p>
                  <p>If through his poverty you are <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8, 9. 1 Tim. 6. 18. Prov. 14. 21.</note> made rich, be rich in good works, and have mercy on the poor.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57120:27"/>
                  <p>If you are releaſed from your ſpiritual Bondage, ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt has made you free, and be not intang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led again with the Yoke of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 1.</note> to ſin, and the luſts of Men.</p>
                  <p>If by Faith you have received Chriſt, and put him on, walk in him, and ſerve him in Holineſs <note place="margin">Col. 2. 6. Luke 1. 75.</note> and Righteouſneſs all the days of your Life.</p>
                  <p>If he has delivered you from Death, live to him who died for <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 15.</note> you, and by death delivered you from Death.</p>
                  <p>Thus by living up to your pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, or doing the Duty of them, you will at laſt receive the benefit of them.</p>
                  <p>It is ſad to want priviledges, but far worſe to abuſe, or not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove them.</p>
                  <p>Make it your great buſineſs to ſecure the ſalvation of your Soul.</p>
                  <p>In order unto it,</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57120:27"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Believe you have a Soul.</item>
                     <item>2. Believe it is precious.</item>
                     <item>3. Live to it, as ſo believing.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. Believe you have a Soul.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Every one has a ſoul, but the Lives of moſt ſhew, that they do not believe it: Some live, as if their Bodies were immortal, and worthy of all their care; and ſome, as if they had no Souls, or as if they were Mortal, and when once dead, ſhould never be alive again. The Soul of ſuch Men is of little more uſe, than (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſays of the Soul of a Swine) to keep the Body from ſtinking. But be you eſtabliſh'd in the belief of this truth, that you have a Soul, and that it is Immortal. A truth that has been own'd by Heathens, and is previous to Religion, for all Religion is grounded upon it. They did uſually ſay, <hi>That to live, was to dye; and to dye, was to live again.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57120:28"/>
                  <q>Poteſt obumbrari, quia non eſt Deus, extingui non poteſt, quia à Deo.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Druydes</hi> made the <hi>Gauls</hi> Valiant, by telling them, that their Souls were Immortal: <hi>Caeſar</hi> put Gold into his Souldiers Pockets, that the fear of loſing it, might make them ſo, and the belief of this Treaſure within you (inclos'd in an Earthen Veſſel, as Manna in an Earthen pot) and the fear of <note place="margin">Exod. 16. 33.</note> loſing it, ſhould provoke you to a diligent care about it, that you may not.</p>
                  <p>A <hi>Sadducee</hi> in Opinion will ſoon <note place="margin">Acts 23. 8.</note> be an Epicure in Life.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Believe that your Soul is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſame Offering was for the Soul of the Poor, that was for <note place="margin">Exod. 30. 15.</note> the Soul of the Rich (half a She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kel was the Soul-money for both) and the Soul of both <hi>(viz.</hi> of a Slave and an Emperour) are alike precious, and (next to that which is infinite and excellent) moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, as will appear,</p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57120:28"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By the Titles given to it.</item>
                     <item>2. By the care taken of it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. By the Titles given to it, <hi>viz.</hi> The breath of Life (Life is a deſirable good, and the Soul a <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 7. Job 2. 4. &amp; 27. 3. <hi>Optimus modus cutis.</hi>
                     </note> moſt precious Being, as it is the breath of Life) Gods Spirit, (God is a Spirit, and ſo is the Soul too, not onely in reſpect of its imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate procedure from him, but in reſpect of its reſemblance to him, a remote Image of God, or an <note place="margin">Prov. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 27.</note> Image of the Trinity, in a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty) the Candle of the Lord (the Sun in the little World, as the Sun is the Soul of the great one) the hidden man (the whole man, or the Man of Man, as <hi>Athens</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Animùs cujuſque eſt quiſque.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 4. 2 Cor. 4. 16. <hi>Pars opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma noſtri.</hi> Job 30. 15. Prov. 4. 7 Pſal. 22. 20.</note> was the <hi>Greece</hi> of <hi>Greece)</hi> Mans principal one, (Wiſdom is the principal thing, and the Soul the ſeat of Wiſdom, Mans principal one) Mans Darling (Chriſt is Gods Darling, Man is Chriſts, and the Soul is Mans) Mans Honour and Excellency; Glory is the manifeſtation of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57120:29"/> and therefore, that which <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nihil mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num in ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>râ, niſi ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo nec in homine, niſi anima.</hi> Gen. 49. 6. Job 4. 21.</note> is his Glory, muſt needs excell.</p>
                  <p>Man was the perfection of the Creation, the Maſter-piece, and chiefeſt part of it, and the Soul the choiceſt part of Man, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by theſe Titles given to it by God, who rates every thing according to its kind and worth; and therefore, ſet the Crown and Diadem by him put upon it, the Letters Teſtimonial ſent from Heaven to commend it, make you highly to value and eſteem of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By the care taken of it.</p>
                  <p>By God and Man, to ſave it, and by the Devil to deſtroy it.</p>
                  <p>By God, <hi>viz.</hi> Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p>By the Father, who in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Wiſdom contriv'd Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for it, inſtituted Sacraments and Ordinances to feed it in this World, provided Heaven a place of Eternal Reſt for it in the World to come, and Angels to guard <note place="margin">Heb. 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> and conduct it ſafe to it.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57120:29"/>
                  <p>By the Son, who in his unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Love laid down his Life as a <note place="margin">Pſal. 49. 7, 8. 1 Pet. 1. 18, 19. <hi>Ex pretio pretium.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 23.</note> Ranſom for it, and parted with his moſt precious Blood as a price to Redeem it.</p>
                  <p>By the Holy Ghoſts powerful Operation in Sanctifying of it, whereby it becomes as Mount <hi>Zion,</hi> the Temple of the moſt High, the Throne of the great King of Heaven, his Manſion, <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 17. Iſa. 57. 15.</note> Dwelling-place, and ſecond Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By Men, <hi>viz.</hi> both good and bad: By good Men, while living, and by bad Men, when dying; <note place="margin">1 King. 21. 20.</note> who, though while living, they ſold themſelves to work Iniquity, and (as by Will) bequeath'd their Souls to the Devil, when dying make void that Will, out of a deſire (for their Souls ſake) to die well, though they would not live ſo.</p>
                  <p>That which is every ones Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, or bears a price every where, and is by all (ſooner or later)
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57120:30"/> highly eſteem'd, and to all alike precious, has worth and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency in it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By the care taken by the Devil to deſtroy it. There are two Lions contend for the Soul; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Leo propter fortitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem advin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendum. Leo propter fertitatem adnocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8.</note> Chriſt, the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> who ſeeks to ſave it; and the Devil, the roaring Lion, who ſeeks to deſtroy it: He is active and diligent, for he goes about ſeeking; bloody and cruel, for he ſeeks to devour: Other Lions prey on dead Bodies, but this on living Souls: He deſired <hi>Job</hi>'s Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for his Souls ſake.</p>
                  <p>If you do not prize your Soul, the Devil does.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Live to your Soul, as believing it is Precious.</p>
                  <p>God might (and that without any Injuſtice) have placed you in the loweſt predicament of the vileſt Creatures; but ſince he has ſtampt his own Image upon you, and given you a Soul, with which you may converſe, not onely with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57120:30"/> Men and Angels, but with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; bleſs him for your Soul, with <note place="margin">Pſal. 103. 1. <hi>Anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> debere,</hi> is the higheſt Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Gen. 49. 3, 4.</note> your Soul, and live to it as a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt excellent and precious.</p>
                  <p>It is your Excellency and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, let it not then conſult its own ſhame, nor (with <hi>Reuben)</hi> loſe its Excellency by ſin, but be Honourably employ'd; ſerve the living God with this breath of Life, (Life muſt be ſerved with Life) worſhip God who is a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit <note place="margin">John 4. 24. Numb. 16. 22.</note> (and the God of the Spirits of all fleſh) with this his Spirit in you.</p>
                  <p>Do not loſe your Soul in looking after its Servant the Body (as <hi>Shimei</hi> loſt his Life in looking af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">1 Kings 2. 36, 37. 38, 39. 40, 41. 46.</note> his) but do your principal work, for this principal one.</p>
                  <p>All that a man has will he give for his life, but life, and all muſt be <note place="margin">Job 2. 4.</note> given and laid out for the good of the Soul.</p>
                  <p>And there is good reaſon for it, if you conſider,</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57120:31"/>
                  <p n="1">1. That your Soul was given to you that you ſhould take care of it, and every thing elſe for the good of your Soul.</p>
                  <p>Every one has not a Child, nor an Eſtate to look after, but every one has a Soul; the pooreſt Widow has theſe two Mites, (a Soul and a Body) and the moſt indigent Beggar this Treaſure: Since then it is every ones (yours as well as their) poſſeſſion, it ſhould be yours, and every ones <note place="margin">Redde ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae, quae ſua ſunt.</note> care, to ſecure the happineſs of it, and therefore, give to the ſoul the things that are the ſouls.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Chriſt likes them beſt, that are moſt careful of their ſouls.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt, when on Earth, lov'd them moſt, who lov'd their ſouls more than his body <hi>(Maries</hi> Breakfaſt was better to him than <hi>Martha's</hi> Dinner) and much more then will he love them that love their ſouls more than their own bodies.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57120:31"/>
                  <p>He that would not have you Murder your Body, would much leſs have you Murder your Soul.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. According to the care for your Soul here, ſo it is like to fare with your Soul and Body here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
                  <p>You are daily Travelling to the Land of Souls, <hi>(viz.</hi> the world of Spirits, both of the juſt and unjuſt) every day you take a ſtep to it, and within a little while you will be all Soul; and as you live to it here, ſo it will be with that, and your Body for ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; the welfar of your Body depends upon the welfare of your Soul, and the eternal welfare of that, upon your care in time about it; and therefore, as by a care for your Soul, you may do two works at once, <hi>(viz.</hi> ſecure the happineſs of Soul and Body) ſo by a neglect of it, will undo both for ever; at the firſt death your <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 14. &amp; 21. 8.</note> Soul ſhall go to Hell, and your Body at the ſecond.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57120:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57120:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:57120:33"/>4. The loſs of the Soul is the greateſt loſs; Chriſt, who beſt knows the worth of a Soul, by the price he paid for it, ſays, that the gain of a whole World (if <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 26.</note> it could be obtain'd) with the loſs of a Soul, would be a gain with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profit, a loſs, rather than a gain, and that not the leaſt, but greateſt, as an irreparable, and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recoverable loſs, a loſs that could neither be made up nor recovered.</p>
                  <p>All other loſſes (even of Life it ſelf) may be made up, either in kind or vertue; but nothing can <note place="margin">Habet ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mortem ſuam cum vitâ beatâ caret, quae vera animae vita dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da eſt.</note> repair, or make up the loſs of the Soul; for in this, God is loſt; a loſt Groat may be found, loſt Time may be redeem'd, and a loſt Eſtate recovered by diligence; but a Soul when gone into Eternity, and loſt, will be for ever ſo; Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven it ſelf <hi>(ſalvâ juſtitiâ)</hi> cannot redeem a Soul fròm Hell when once there.</p>
                  <p>Your Soul is Gods as well as <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 20.</note> your Body, that he has bought,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57120:33"/> and therefore Glorifie him with it, and commit the keeping of it to him in well-doing, as unto a faithful Creator, of Souls, as well as of Bodies, that at laſt it may <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 19. Heb. 12. 22, 23.</note> be taken up to the innumerable Company of Spirits, <hi>viz.</hi> of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels created perfect, and of juſt Men made ſo.</p>
                  <p>Begin the work of Religion early.</p>
                  <p>Make it the great buſineſs of your Life.</p>
                  <p>Be hearty and ſincere in it.</p>
                  <p>Be true and faithful to it, to the end of your Life.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Begin the work early.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. God commands and expects it.</item>
                     <item>2. It is the beſt time for it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">(1.) God commands and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cain</hi> brought Fruit to God (an <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 3. 4.</note> Offering of the Fruit of the Ground) <hi>Abel</hi> brought firſt fruits, (the firſtlings of his Flock) and God had reſpect to <hi>Abel</hi> and his
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57120:34"/> Offering, but not to <hi>Cains,</hi> and this before the ſpecial Law of <note place="margin">Exod. 13. 2. &amp; 22. 29. &amp; 34. 26.</note> firſt-fruits, and firſt-born (which were Gods in all) was made, to ſhew (as is uſually obſerv'd) that it was not Ceremonial, but Moral and perpetual.</p>
                  <p>God, or the Devil, will have the uſe and ſervice of your Life, but God has the greateſt Right to it; and his will is not onely for work, but for Day, and Time, and the firſt of that <hi>(viz.</hi> your <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 1.</note> Youth) he calls for, which ſhews kindneſs on his part (in taking any into his Service before they can well work for him) and ſhould promote Obedience on yours. God is the faſhioner and former, <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 13, 14, 15, 16. Deut. 32. 18. Pſal. 71. 17. Jer. 3. 4.</note> the teacher and preſerver, the guide and ſtrength of your Youth, all the parts, Beauty, Strength, and all the other Excellencies of it, come from him, and ought to be employ'd for him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do not give the Devil your Youth, and God your Old Age;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57120:34"/> him your Spring, and God your Winter; him your Vintage, and God your Gleanings; him your Flower, and God your Bran; him the beſt, and God the worſt; but the beſt, for he is beſt, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves the beſt.</p>
                  <p>Not an old or rotten Sacrifice, <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 8, 14.</note> but the fatteſt, and faireſt muſt be laid upon Gods Altar.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) It is the beſt time for it. <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 1. The time of your Choices. <hi>Primum in unoquoque generè eſt perfect iſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>As to Eaſe, Honour, Service, Comforts, and Safety.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. As to Eaſe.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Old Age is the beſt for Advice and Counſel, but Youth the beſt for Action, both as to the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Moral frame of the Body and Mind, <hi>viz.</hi> the parts of one, and the endowments of the other. Old Age is called the Sickneſs of Nature, but Youth is the Health and Strength of it; that is called <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 1.</note> the evil day (not onely in reſpect of the evil then ſuffered, but of the indiſpoſition from that evil, to any thing that is good) but
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57120:35"/> this a good day, as moſt fit and proper for work; the Body being moſt active and vigorous, the Fancy and Invention moſt quick, the Memory moſt ſtrong, the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections moſt ſmart and lively, the Conſcience moſt pure, the Will moſt pliable, and the Heart (as not hardened by Cuſtom in ſin) moſt ſoft, and ſo moſt fit to receive the impreſſions of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
                  <p>Trees are tranſplanted, Horſes broken, and Cattel accuſtomed to the Yoke with eaſe, when young; and Youth more fit for Inſtruction, than Old Age, even then, when it is ſcarce fit for any thing elſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. As to Honour.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Piety in Youth will give you Honour with God and Men.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. With God.</label> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30. Luke 13. 6, 7.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>You are Planted in a Vineyard, and God expects Fruit from you as ſoon as you are Planted; he looks for it (in the Spring) and when he
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57120:35"/> finds it, takes notice of it (as he did of the kindneſs of <hi>Iſraels</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 2.</note> Youth) and is greatly pleaſed with it (as Chriſt with the Rich <note place="margin">Mark 10. 20, 21.</note> Man in the Goſpel, that from his Youth obſerved the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) for he loves to magnifie <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 2.</note> his praiſe out of the mouths of Babes and Sucklings.</p>
                  <p>The Almond-tree that bloſſom'd <note place="margin">Numb. 17. 8.</note> ſooneſt, was put into the Ark, and <hi>John,</hi> the youngeſt Diſciple, was moſt beloved.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. With Men.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was the Glory of <hi>Alexander,</hi> not ſo much that he Conquer'd the World, as that he did it in his Youth. A Crown (better than one of Gold) on <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s Head, that he was Religious in his ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <note place="margin">2 Chron. 34. 1. 2.</note> Years: The Honour of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> (they lived and died in Honour) and of <hi>Daniel</hi> (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Dan. 9. 23.</note> a Man of deſires) becauſe Religious in Youth; and ſo it will be of all the Children of Wiſdom, when found walking early, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57120:36"/> well as late, in the ways of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Fruits early ripe, are by all greatly priz'd.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. As to Service.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>The moſt eminent in God's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice were (as is to be ſeen upon Record) moſt early at it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a Religious Child in his Fathers Houſe, was afterwards a Religious Senator in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Samuel,</hi> a Religious Child, was an eminent Prophet, Recorded by <hi>David,</hi> and by God himſelf, <note place="margin">Pſal. 99. 6. Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 15. 1.</note> as one (that if any he) could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with God by Prayer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Joſiah,</hi> a Religious Child (at <note place="margin">2 King. 23. 25.</note> eight years old) and a Renowned King, for there was none like to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Timothy,</hi> a Religious Child, was <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 15.</note> afterwards eminent in the Service of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>And Chriſt more eminent than <note place="margin">Luke 2. 12, 9.</note> all, went early about his Fathers buſineſs.</p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:57120:36"/>
                  <p>So that if you would be uſeful in Life, you muſt be Religious in Youth: The ſooner Weeds are pull'd up, the better the Corn will grow; and the ſooner you are good, the more good you will do: Therefore, if you would have your Age be the Harveſt, your Youth muſt be the Seed-time.</p>
                  <p>The good Figs were ſooneſt <note place="margin">Jer. 24. 2.</note> ripe.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label>4. As to Comfort.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Timothy,</hi> that was Godly from <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2: 22.</note> his Youth, was bid <hi>to flee Youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Luſts;</hi> and ſurely then it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you (and all that are young) to do ſo, that you may not lay a Foundation for ſin or ſorrow (or for both) in Old Age.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. For Sin.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Youth, of all the Ages of Life, is moſt ſubject, as to Infection in Body, ſo to Corruption in Soul.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Solomon</hi> beheld a Young Man <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 7.</note> void of Underſtanding; and it was the younger Brother (not
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57120:37"/> the elder) that was the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal. <note place="margin">Luke 15. 12, 13.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Youth is to this Life, as this Life is to that to come; as this Life is (well or ill) ordered, ſo it is like to be with you for ever in that; and as your Youth is, ſo the ſequel of your Life is like to <note place="margin">Maturè fias ſenex. utdiu ſenex. <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 10, 11.</note> be; and therefore it concerns you to be good then, that it may (like the firſt-fruits to the Harveſt) Sanctifie the remainder of your Life.</p>
                  <p>All Habits are by ſo much the more firmly radicated in their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, by how much the Actions from whence they come, are the more frequently and timely uſed.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. For Sorrow.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Impiety in Youth will increaſe ſin in Age (for by Cuſtom it will become Natural) and that will increaſe ſorrow; for, as bruiſes in Youth, bring aches in Old Age; ſo ſins in Youth will bring ſorrow then; and therefore give God now the poſſeſſion of your Youth,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57120:37"/> that you may not then (with <note place="margin">Job 13. 26. Pſal. 25. 7. Jer. 31. 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Job, David,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim)</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs the ſins of it.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <label>5. As to Safety, in that,</label>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Your time is uncertain.</item>
                     <item>2. The work (by delay) will be more difficult.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Your time is uncertain.</p>
                  <p>It is true, Old Age will not come preſently, nor may not, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, to you at all; (you are not ſure you ſhall live to be Old) but Death will come ſooner or later; the longer your Glaſs has been running, the leſs there is to run, and it may be out before you are aware, for it is ever running, and there are no ſtops in it.</p>
                  <p>There are young Skulls as well as old ones in <hi>Golgotha;</hi> and there is a dying in Youth, as certainly <note place="margin">Job 36. 14.</note> as in Old Age.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The work (by delay) will be more difficult.</p>
                  <p>The longer you defer the work, like the deferring to buy the <hi>Sybil's</hi> Propheſies, the dearer (as one
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57120:38"/> obſerves) every day it will coſt you; <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> on Hoſ. 14. 2.</note> the more Tears, the harder Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the deeper ſorrows, and the ſtronger cries, and thereby become Morally (though not ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely) impoſſible; you will not have leſs work to do by delay, <note place="margin">Jer. 13. 23.</note> but more work, and leſs time.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Cripple onely, that <note place="margin">John 5. 4.</note> went into the Pool of <hi>Betheſda</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the troubling of the Waters, was healed.</p>
                  <p>I have read of a Temple (in <hi>Spain)</hi> Dedicated to Old Age; I wiſh your Young Age may be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated <note place="margin">Exod. 33. 11.</note> (as <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s) to Gods Temple, and the Service of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The glory of Young Men</hi> (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 20. 29.</note> ſays) <hi>is their ſtrength,</hi> and the glory of that glory, is to give that ſtrength, the excellency of that Power (as <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid of his firſt-born <hi>Reuben)</hi> to Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. If you begin early, the <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 3.</note> Progreſs will be happy, and the end comfortable. You cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin too ſoon nor hold out too late.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:57120:38"/>
                  <p n="2">2. Make Religion the great bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs <note place="margin">Luke 16. 11. Luke 10. 42. <hi>Non repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit, ſed diſtinguit.</hi>
                     </note> of your Life.</p>
                  <p>Religion is the true riches, the good eminenter part, <hi>(Martha's</hi> work was good, but <hi>Mary's</hi> was better,) the whole Duty of Man, his Form, Being, and Eſſence, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 13. Pſ. 111. <hi>ult. Totus eſt perfectus animo homo omne homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis bonum. &amp; finis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min is.</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 22. <hi>Semper, &amp; ad ſemper.</hi> Prov 28. 14. Deut. 32. 47. Prov, 4. 7. Eph. 4. 1. Phil. 2. 12. Jer. 7. 22, 23.</note> his Wiſdom, and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal thing, his Happineſs, his Calling, and Work, a Work moſt ſutable to him, moſt uſeful and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous (his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt as well as his Duty) his chief work (above all Natural, Politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, Moral, and Ceremonial work) the one thing needful, never out of ſeaſon, but (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſays of Philoſophy) at all times neceſſary; his Life, and principal end of his Life, other things are but means to this end; and therefore this muſt be preferred and ſet before it.</p>
                  <p>The end is more excellent than the means.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:57120:39"/>
                  <p>Since then it is ſo in it ſelf, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Sapiens ſemper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit à fine.</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 31.</note> let it be ſo to you, mind it as your chief good (the ſupream end, and chief good are one) refer all the general and particular actions of your Life to it ultimately, (the end makes the means lovely) make all other <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Finis dat amabilitatem medis, finis impeliit agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, finis eſt ſumme ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petibilis, finis ultimus dat ordinem &amp; menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</hi> Prov. 6. 21. Pſ. 63. 8. Numb. 6. 14, 24. Eccleſ. 9. 10. Rom. 12. 11. 1 Tim. 5. 10. Mat. 6. 33. Pſal. 63. 1.</note> things ſubſervient to it, and let this as Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Chief, give Laws to all, carry the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it always in your mind, place it next to your Heart, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt in your thoughts; be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in it, and proſecute the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of it both fully, and earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly, not as the laſt and leaſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs of your Life, but as the firſt and greateſt <hi>(viz.</hi> in order and dignity) not ſecondarily, but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, before all other things, and above them.</p>
                  <p>Two principal ends can never conſiſt together.</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:57120:39"/>
                  <p>Two things may encourage you to this work, and in it.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Strength is promiſed to it.</item>
                     <item>2. A Reward attends it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Strength is promiſed to it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tripho</hi> the <hi>Jew,</hi> in his Diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> tells him, that thoſe Precepts Chriſt left about the Duties of Religion, were ſo harſh and burdenſome, that he would have but few, if any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples; and many there are, that either through miſtake think they find this ſtumbling-block in the way of Religion, and cannot get over it, or lay it there, and will not; it is true, to carnal minds by reaſon of the contrariety of their Nature to Religion, through <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 14, 22.</note> the corruption that is in them, and by reaſon of cuſtom in ſin, which makes the contrariety ſtronger, the work's difficult and uneaſie; but to them that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, it is not, or if ſo at firſt, yet by uſe it becomes pleaſant and delightful, for Chriſts Yoke by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57120:40"/> conſtant wearing, grows eaſie. <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 29.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>Grave, dum tollis, ſuave, cum tuleris.</q>
                  <p>But if it were not ſo, yet ſtrength ſhall be given to it, that will make it ſo. In the Body, where there is a vein to convey Blood, there is an Artery to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey Spirits; and in the Scripture, <note place="margin">Deut. 10. 16. &amp; 30. 6. Phil. 2. 12, 13.</note> where there is a Command to work, there is a promiſe of ſtrength to it; what is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in one place, is a Promiſe in another.</p>
                  <p>Now, difficult work and eaſie, are both alike, if a ſutable, and proportionable ſtrength be given <note place="margin">Ezek. 18. 31. &amp; 36. 26.</note> to the performance of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Reward attends it, <hi>viz.</hi> Of <hi>Honour, Pleaſure, Profit,</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. Of Honour.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was no way to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Honour (among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 45. 9. &amp; 149. 9.</note> but through the Temple of Vertue; nor is there any
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57120:40"/> coming to Honour now in the <note place="margin">Prov. 13. 5. &amp; 14. 34. 1 Theſ. 4. 4. Rom. 6. 21.</note> broad way of ſin, but in the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row way of Religion; for as the future iſſue of ſin is Death, ſo the preſent fruit is ſhame.</p>
                  <p>Indeed the Enemies of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (who fetch their Scutcheon out of the Devils Herald-Office) count ſin their Honour, and glory in their ſhame; but God (who is the Fountain of all true Honour) <note place="margin">Prov. 21. 21.</note> places it in Righteouſneſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, he is Glorious in Holineſs, and if it be his Honour, it may well be eſteemed yours; this is <note place="margin">John 5. 44.</note> the onely true Honour, and it cometh from God only, and if by <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> this you Honour him, you ſhall be everlaſtingly honoured by him; a Spirit of Glory ſhall reſt on you <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 14.</note> here, and a Crown of Glory be put upon you hereafter.</p>
                  <p>All ſeek Honour, and ſome to <note place="margin">Honor cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car babet.</note> the loſs of their Lives and Souls, but none but the Religious truly find it.</p>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:57120:41"/>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Of Pleaſure.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Enemies of Religion think, if once they eſpouſe the profeſſion of it, that all Joy and Mirth muſt be caſt out, (as the Minſtrels were by Chriſt out of the Rulers Houſe, when he came to raiſe his <note place="margin">Mat. 9. 23, 25.</note> Daughter to Life) but they are much miſtaken, for Chriſt (the increated wiſdom of the Father) <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 24. Prov. 3. 17.</note> ſays, that the ways of wiſdom have pleaſure in them; not the end onely, but the way, and not ſome one way onely, but all the ways, and every ſtep in them, are, not onely pleaſant, but pleaſantneſs, yea, pleaſantneſſes; having all pleaſures that are good, both as to kind and degree in it. The Sheep has delights as well as the Swine, though it wallows not (with the Swine) in the mire; and the Religious their pleaſures, though none that are vain and ſenſual.</p>
                  <p>All look for pleaſure in Life, and moſt think there is no Life without it; but the Religious only find it.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:57120:41"/>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. Of Profit.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>Religion brings gain, this the <note place="margin">Job 1. 9. 10. 1 Tim. 6. 6.</note> Devil could not deny, when he accuſed <hi>Job</hi> of Hypocriſie (now the praiſe of an Enemy is, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 4.</note> ſays, a univerſal good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port) and this God has aſſured <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 28. 29. Mark 10. 29, 30.</note> to all the ſincere Profeſſors and Friends of it, and that no ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gain neither, but an increaſe greater than the World can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or ſecure, for it is a hundred fold, not ten in the hundred, but a hundred upon ten, a hundred to one (uſe upon uſe) <hi>viz.</hi> either in kind or vertue in this World, and in the World to come, Life eternal.</p>
                  <p>You may loſe ſomething for <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 33. 1 Cor. 3. 22, 23.</note> Religion, but you ſhall never loſe any thing by it; for, if God be yours, all things are yours; all things conditionally, if he abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely.</p>
                  <p>The Offerings of Old increaſed <note place="margin">2 Chron. 31. 9, 10.</note> their ſtore.</p>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:57120:42"/>
                  <p n="4">
                     <label>4. Of Peace.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Enemies of Religion talk <note place="margin">Prov. 3. 7, 17. Pſal. 119. 165.</note> much of their Peace, but without any Reaſon, for there is no Peace to them in that, they are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the God of Peace, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Spirit of Peace (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without Peace the fruit of <note place="margin">Iſa. 48. 22.</note> the Spirit) and Fighters againſt Chriſt the Prince of Peace, who ſpeaks Peace, not to his Enemies that commit folly, but to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects <note place="margin">Pſal. 85. 8.</note> that return no more to it.</p>
                  <p>Joy (as the Philoſopher ſays) is the ſhadow of all Vertue, (as inſeparable perhaps from it, as the ſhadow from the Body) and the fruit of Righteouſneſs (as the Apoſtle ſays) is Peace, there is <note place="margin">James 3. 18. Rom. 3. 17.</note> no Peace without it, and all true Peace in it, and it is worth the having; for it abides, not onely in Life, but at Death too. <hi>The end of the upright is Peace.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 37. 37.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Peace in Life is a rare Bleſſing, but at Death a greater; and was there no other benefit in this
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57120:42"/> World to be got by Religion, it is enough to make you in love with it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Be hearty and ſincere in the work of Religion.</p>
                  <p>When you enter upon the work of Religion, let that enter into you, and give up, not onely your Name, but Heart to it; and what <note place="margin">Acts 11. 23. Eph. 6. 6.</note> ever you do in it, do it heartily to the Lord.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Nothing will be accepted without the Heart.</item>
                     <item>2. Any thing will be accepted with it.</item>
                     <item>3. Your Heart is Gods by right.</item>
                     <item>4. God calls for it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Nothing will be accepted without the Heart.</p>
                  <p>The Heart is the Fountain and Principle of Spiritual as well as Natural Life, and that which gives Life to all. The Tree in the midſt <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 3.</note> of the Garden (all of pith) the choice Sacrifice (the Male in the <note place="margin">Mal. 1. 14.</note> Flock) the fat of the Sacrifice that he reſerves to himſelf; the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57120:43"/> belov'd above any, and the <note place="margin">John 20. 2. Gen. 43. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Benjamin,</hi> without which nothing will be accepted; and therefore this muſt be the Treaſure you <note place="margin">Mat. 2. 11.</note> open, when you bring your Gift unto him.</p>
                  <p>You know no more than you do in Religion, and do no more, than what you do with the Heart, for, when things are not true, they are not at all.</p>
                  <q>Ens &amp; verum connectuntur.</q>
                  <p n="2">2. Any thing will be accepted with it.</p>
                  <p>Affections ſhall be interpreted <note place="margin">1 Kings 8. 18. Pſal. 32. 5.</note> Actions, and Purpoſes Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; the will ſhall paſs for the work, imperfect Duties for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect (a little, or any thing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,) ſo it be all you have, and <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 12.</note> the Heart be in them, for the heart is Gods Sacrifice, yea, his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, all, and every one, the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 17.</note> Power, and Value of all, in one, and that which ingratiates all.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:57120:43"/>
                  <p>God ſometimes accepts the will for the deed, but at all times the will more than the deed.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Your Heart is Gods by right.</p>
                  <p>It is Gods more than yours, and <note place="margin">Mark 12. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. 1 Cor. 6. <hi>ult.</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 18, 19. Prov. 23. 26.</note> therefore be juſt, and give him that which is his own, for he bought it, and dearly paid for it.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt parted with his Heart blood, to have the love and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of yours.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. God calls for your Heart.</p>
                  <p>He deſires it, wooes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treats, wiſhes and waits for it, <note place="margin">Iſa. 1 2.</note> yea, commands it, and not to give it, is to Rebel againſt him.</p>
                  <p>God has ever been a giver to you, and now deſires to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver from you; he has often given you the deſire of your Heart, let him then have from you the deſire of his, and as he deſires it, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <label>1. Willingly.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſtole away the Hearts <note place="margin">2 Sam 15. 5, 6.</note> of ſome of the Men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but God accepts of none but ſuch as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:57120:44"/> (with the Men of <hi>Iſrael)</hi> of a <note place="margin">Exod. 25. 2. &amp; 35. 5.</note> willing Heart give themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <label>2. Fully.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>One and the ſame Temple could not receive the Ark and <hi>Dagon;</hi> nor can God and the Devil have <note place="margin">1 Sam. 5. 3, 4.</note> your Heart at one and the ſame time, one of them will have it, both at once cannot, nor God at any time truly, unleſs wholly; he is but one, and he will be own'd <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 37. <hi>Aut Caeſar, aut nullus.</hi> Exod. 29. 18. Pſal. 51. 19.</note> as one; none muſt ſhare with him in it (for he admits no Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val) nor muſt any part of it be kept from him, for he will have all (a whole Burnt-offering) or nothing.</p>
                  <p>Unleſs all be given, nothing is truly given.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <label>3. Conſtantly.</label>
                  </p>
                  <p>You muſt not give your Heart one day to Religion, and another day to Sin; one day to Gods Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and on another to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, but to God onely, and to him for ever.</p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:57120:44"/>
                  <p>By thus giving your Heart to God, you will gain his; for he <note place="margin">John 14. 21.</note> that loveth him, ſhall be loved of him.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Be true and faithful to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to the end of your Life.</p>
                  <p>You muſt not onely begin, but proceed in the work of Religion, and not onely proceed, but end in it; and there is good reaſon for it, in that,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Honour of God and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is concern'd in it.</item>
                     <item>2. Your Salvation depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. The Honour of God and Religion is concerned in it.</p>
                  <p>Stedfaſtneſs in Religion is a credit to Religion, and to God the Maſter of it, (he owns it ſo) but a departure from it, tacitly accuſes Religion of unpleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the Maſter of it of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, (as if there was Iniquity in him) it ſays in effect, that either the work is not good, and not fit to be done, or the Maſter
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57120:45"/> not good, and not fit to be ſerv'd; which is a greater Reproach to him than if he had never been ſerv'd. A diſhonour that the Heathen offer not to their Idols <note place="margin">Jer. 2. 11.</note> (for they change not their gods) a ſin that grieves him to the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Heart; yea, a ſin ſo great, that he looks upon it as impardonable <hi>(how ſhall I Pardon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>thee for this?)</hi> for he hates an Apoſtate as bad, if not worſe, than a <hi>Sodomite.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No comlier ſight in Gods Eyes, than young Diſciples, and old ones, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are early and late at his work.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Your Salvation depends up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
                  <p>If you are not ſo Religious as <note place="margin">2 John 8.</note> others, you ſhall not have ſo full a Reward as they; but if you be not ſtedfaſt in it, you ſhall have <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 9. Prov. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 18. Heb. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>5.</note> none at all It is true, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward is both ſure and great, but it is promiſed to none but them that work, nor to any of them,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57120:45"/> unleſs they are unmoveable, and always abounding in it; the peny <note place="margin">Luk. 9. 62.</note> is for them, not that enter into the Vineyard, but for them that abide there until Night; and the Crown for them, not that ſtart well, but that run ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> not to the middle onely, but to the end of the Race. And therefore you muſt be ſtedfaſt, and always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding in Labour, if you would <note place="margin">1 Cor 15. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> not labour in vain; and not (with the <hi>Iſraelites)</hi> ſtand ſtill, nor go <note place="margin">Exod. 14. 13.</note> back, but forward, if you would ſee the Salvation of God.</p>
                  <p>Every Grace adorns a Chriſtian, Perſeverance onely crowns him. <note place="margin">Rev. 2. 10.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, that you may</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Conſider what the work of Religion is, before you engage in <note place="margin">Luke 14. 28, 29, 30.</note> it.</p>
                  <p>There is a Croſs to be found in the way of Religion, as well as a Crown at the end of it; and therefore if you unadviſedly enter upon it, without conſidering what it is, or what it may coſt you,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57120:46"/> you may meet with a difficulty that will make way for Apoſtaſie. A thing well reſolv'd is half done, but never well reſolv'd, unleſs firſt conſidered; and therefore this is the firſt thing you muſt do, fail in this, and you will fail in all.</p>
                  <p>If an Arithmetician miſtake in his firſt figure, the whole Account will be wrong.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Take not up a profeſſion of Religion to ſerve your worldly Intereſt or Advantage.</p>
                  <p>Sin upon no mans account what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, <hi>(Calliſthenes</hi> would not pledge <hi>Alexander,</hi> to have need of <hi>Aeſculapius)</hi> nor be not Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious upon that ſcore onely, (as <hi>Joaſh</hi> was, for <hi>Jehoiada</hi>'s ſake, <note place="margin">2 Chron. 24. 17, 18.</note> while he lived) for if that be all, your Religion is little worth, and you may as quickly loſe it, as find it; they that follow Chriſt for <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nunc ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, nunc illarum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidus,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> of <hi>Ant.</hi>
                     </note> Loaves, will leave him when they are ſpent and gone; and they that are for any Religion (becauſe in faſhion) either are of none, or will eaſily be ſo.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57120:46"/>
                  <p>It is better to be of no Religion, than of every one.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Beware of the leaſt degree of remiſneſs in Religion, either in Judgment or Affection.</p>
                  <p>A Gangreen goes on by degrees, (firſt, one part or Member is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, and then another) and ſo does Apoſtacy; it begins in the Judgment, and if that diſeſteems Religion, the Affections will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline <note place="margin">Voluntas ſequitur dictamen intellectus.</note> and forſake it, the Affections follow the Judgment, and what that lightly approves of, the other will as coldly and indifferently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive.</p>
                  <p>He that is careleſs of little ſlips, is in danger of a fall.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Be much in the uſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the publick and private Duties of Religion.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are (as one ſays) the Sphere of Grace, and in theſe conſiſts the life of Religion; and therefore, if nothing of them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in your Life, or if you live in the neglect of them, or are
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57120:47"/> negligent in them, your pretended Religion will ſoon vaniſh, and come to nothing.</p>
                  <p>If once you become formal in Devotion, you will quickly be any thing in Converſation.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Be eſtabliſhed in the Faith.</p>
                  <p>It is true, Fear is the Grace that keeps you in your ſtanding, (and <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 14. 1 Cor. 10. 12. 2 Cor. 1. <hi>ult.</hi> Eph. 4. 4. Col. 2. 7.</note> therefore, if you would never fall, you muſt ever fear,) but Faith is the Grace by which you ſtand, for it unites you to Chriſt, in whom you are preſerv'd; and therefore, be well rooted and grounded in it.</p>
                  <p>If you be carried away with <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 7. 1 Pet. 1. 5.</note> every wind of Doctrine, you will at laſt be true and ſted faſt to none; but if you are eſtabliſhed in the Doctrine of Faith, and grow in the Grace of Faith; if you live the life of Faith, and keep the Doctrine of Faith, you will be ſafe; for if you keep the Faith, the Faith will keep you.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57120:47"/>
                  <head>Of Original Sin.</head>
                  <p>It is an Ancient Tradition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> that when <hi>Noah</hi> ſent forth his Sons to people the World, he gave to every one of them ſome Reliques of <hi>Adam;</hi> but it is a more certain and anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent truth, that all the Poſterity of <hi>Adam</hi> have receiv'd, not onely ſome, but all the Reliques of his ſinful Corruption, a leaven that has overſpread the whole lump of Mankind, for all have corrupted their ways <hi>(viz.</hi> all except Chriſt) <note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1.</note> and all that is done by them, and all that is in them <hi>(viz.</hi> all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of their Souls, all the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 18.</note> of their Bodies, and the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of each) are defiled by it. <note place="margin">Tria <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinus</hi> tribuit pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nali quod ſic pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, poena peccati, cauſa pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>A Toads poyſon is but in one place, but this is in all, like a Diſeaſe that has corrupted the whole Maſs of Blood.</p>
                  <p>By this you are indiſpos'd to all good, for there is nothing in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57120:48"/> World, but it will either find as a hindrance to it, or make it ſo.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>Paul</hi> had a will to work, <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17. Rom. 7. 18.</note> he wanted a power.</p>
                  <p>By this you are inclin'd to all evil.</p>
                  <p>There is not a ſin in Hell, but has a Root in this; nor any ſin ſo great or foul, but you would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, if under the power of it, and left to your ſelf; for it is virtually all ſin.</p>
                  <p>The new Man (the new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 17. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> is not ſo much one Grace, as all; and the Old Man (Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſin) is not ſo much one ſin, as all.</p>
                  <p>So that here you may ſee,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What cauſe you have to be humbled under it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plato</hi> ſays, if Vertue could be ſeen with Bodily Eyes, it would Raviſh the Beholders; and if the Corruption in all by Nature could be ſeen, it would (as the Schools ſay) tranſport them to Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:57120:48"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> were humbled <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 5. Rom. 7. 24.</note> under it, therefore and well may you.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Where to lay the blame, when you ſin.</p>
                  <p>Some, when fallen under af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictive Evil, lay all on Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and nothing on Sin that cauſed it; and when fallen into ſin, lay all on the Devil, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing on themſelves; and thereby make the Devil (to whom due ſhould be given) worſe than he is, and themſelves better than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are; for were there no Devil to tempt to ſin, there is that within them, that both can, and would do it.</p>
                  <p>Since then the Devil cannot prevail, unleſs you yield to him, (for his ſtrength is within you) let the time of Complaint againſt him, be ſpent in reſiſting of him, that you may not.</p>
                  <p>It is the Bello<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and fire, that makes fire.</p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:57120:49"/>
                  <p>And ſince you are, when drawn aſide, enticed by your own Luſts, <note place="margin">James 1. 14, 15.</note> (the Enemies within you) let all the actions of ſin be laid at the door of your own Heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>David,</hi> though a Man after Gods Heart, ſometimes walk'd <note place="margin">1 Chron. 21. 1, 17.</note> after his own, yet then he laid the blame, not on the Devil, but on himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What little cauſe you have to cenſure any when fallen into ſin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plato</hi>'s Advice to his Scholars was, that when they ſaw any ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular, and exorbitant in their Lives, they ſhould not raſhly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure them, but reflect on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and conſider, if they were not, or had not been ſuch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And it is the Advice of St. <hi>Paul</hi> (a greater than <hi>Plato)</hi> when any are overtaken in a fault, not to inſult over them, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> them in a Spirit of Meekneſs, (to ſet them in Joynt) and there is good reaſon for it; for though
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57120:49"/> all are not alike evil by practice, yet all being by Nature ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Aut ſumus aut ſuimus aut poſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus eſſe quod hic eſt.</note> ſeminally, and diſpoſitively the ſame, they either have done, or may do ſo.</p>
                  <p>The worſt mens actions ſhew what the beſt men by Nature are inclin'd to.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of your own ſin, and of the ſins of others.</head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Of your own ſin.</head>
                     <p>IN every body there is ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant Humour, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one there is a ſin that may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called their ſin, more than the ſin of any other, or than any other ſin, that they themſelves are inclin'd to.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">This ſin is either,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That ſin you are moſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to; the Devil knows the ſin that you (and all) are by diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition (as well as by cuſtom and calling) moſt inclin'd to, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57120:50"/> how to accommodate and ſute his Temptation to it.</p>
                     <p>Now, that ſin you are moſt fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently tempted to, that is your ſin.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. The captivating conquering ſin, againſt which you are moſt weak, and by which (as <hi>Samſon</hi> by <hi>Delilah)</hi> you are moſt eaſily <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 12. Ezek. 16. 30. Rom. 6. 16. 2 Pet. 2. 19.</note> overcome.</p>
                     <p>You are moſt his, who is Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter over you, and whoſe Servant you are.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That ſin you are moſt tender of, and indulgent to, that ſin you <note place="margin">Judges. 6. 31.</note> defend, and moſt excuſe.</p>
                     <p>We always take the part of them we love.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That ſin you make moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for, for which any thing <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 14.</note> ſhall be given, and to which any thing ſhall be Sacrificed.</p>
                     <p>The beſt Friends are ever beſt provided for.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Or that ſin which is moſt highly eſteemed of <hi>(viz.</hi> as a right Hand, and a right Eye)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57120:50"/> that has the Throne of the Heart, and Commands in Chief that which the thoughts and deſires are moſt buſied about, and moſt approve, affect, and follow after. <note place="margin">Jer. 22. 7. Hoſ. 4. 8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Affections make any thing moſt our own.</p>
                     <p>This is a ſin againſt knowledge, (and of all ſins the principal) a ſin, that ſhews, not onely the Communion of the Heart with it, but the Union alſo of the Heart to it, and the greater becauſe ſo; for, the more a ſin is againſt Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the more there is of the Heart in it, the greater it is; and therefore, above all (either great or ſmall) you muſt reſiſt and oppoſe it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> prov'd his uprightneſs <note place="margin">Pſal. 18. 23.</note> before God by this, <hi>viz.</hi> that he had kept himſelf from his Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and you cannot be ſincere un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you do ſo too.</p>
                     <p>That ſin you love moſt, God hates moſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:57120:51"/>
                     <head>Of other mens ſins.</head>
                     <p>Merchants can Trade in bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms that are not their own; and a Trade in ſin may be driven by you, by other mens ſins as well as your own; and then it is, when either you adviſe, or provoke them to ſin, conſent to it, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge them in it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jonadab</hi> was guilty of <hi>Amnon</hi>'s <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13. 5.</note> uncleanneſs with <hi>Tamar, Ahitophel</hi> of <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s with his Fathers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 21, 22.</note> for they advis'd them to it; and the Chief Prieſts and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> were guilty of Chriſts death, <note place="margin">John 11. 47, 53.</note> for they ſat in Council about it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sapphira</hi> was guilty of the ſin <note place="margin">Acts 5. 1, 2.</note> of <hi>Ananias</hi> (for though ſhe kept not back part of the price, yet ſhe was privy to it) and <hi>Saul</hi> of <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Death, (for he conſented <note place="margin">Acts 22. 20. &amp; 26. 10.</note> to it, and kept the Raiment of them that ſlew him) and of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others that were put to Death, for he gave his voice againſt them.</p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:57120:51"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jezebel</hi> was guilty of <hi>Ahab</hi>'s ſin, <note place="margin">1 King. 21. 7, 25.</note> and of <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Death, for ſhe ſtirred up <hi>Ahab</hi> to it. <hi>Balaam</hi> and <note place="margin">2 King. 17. 21. Numb. 23. 14. &amp; 25. 1. Rev. 2. 14.</note> 
                        <hi>Jeroboam</hi> were guilty of <hi>Iſraels</hi> Idolatry, for they provoked them to it; and <hi>Eli,</hi> of the ſin of his Sons, in that he reſtrained them not, when they made themſelves vile; a ſin ſo great, that it was <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3. 11, 12, 13, 14.</note> not to be purged with Sacrifice.</p>
                     <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe many ways by which others have been (and by which you may be) guilty of the ſins of others; and therefore, it concerns you to avoid them, that you may not.</p>
                     <p>It is bad to ſin of your ſelf, but worſe to adviſe others to it, for it ſhews a great ripeneſs in ſin.</p>
                     <p>Flowers and Herbs, when ripe, ſhed their Seed.</p>
                     <p>By conſenting to the ſin of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you diſcover a will to act it, if you had Opportunity, and are equally guilty with them.</p>
                     <p>The Receiver is as bad as the <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 18.</note> Thief.</p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:57120:52"/>
                     <p>By provoking others to ſin, you will provoke God to vengeance againſt them, and your ſelf too.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Jeroboam</hi> cauſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin, and it was the Ruine both of him <note place="margin">1 King. 13. 34.</note> and them.</p>
                     <p>To defend ſin, is a high degree of ſinning, and to indulge it, is not the leaſt.</p>
                     <p>To indulge the leaſt ſin, ſome ſay, is as bad as the commiſſion of the greateſt, if not, yet the leaſt ſin indulg'd becomes great.</p>
                     <p>The non-execution of God's Law againſt ſin, is an open, and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent breach of it.</p>
                     <p>He that does not puniſh ſin <note place="margin">Qui non prohibet. Jubet.</note> (when his Duty and Place ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges to it) Commands it.</p>
                     <p>Therefore, never either ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or openly, in will, or in word, by permiſſion, or approbation, flattery or applauſe, conſent to the ſin of another; nor either al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure, or entice, incenſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke any to ſin, but either reſtrain them from it, or reprove them
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57120:52"/> for it, that you may (with <hi>Paul)</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Acts 20. 26. <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> be pure from the Blood, and clear from the guilt of the ſins of all with whom you converſe.</p>
                     <p>If any Miſchief happened (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law) either to Man or Beaſt fallen into a Pit, he was guilty, that ſaw the Pit open, and did not cover it; and ſo will you be of the ſin of another, though not acted by you, if not prevented by you (ſo far as you are able) before it is committed, or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved and condemned, when it is.</p>
                     <p>Now, that you may not ſpoil Gods Cauſe with ill Pleading, nor become an Advocate for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, when (by the reproof of ſin) you appear one for God, you muſt do it</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Seaſonably.</item>
                        <item>2. Speedily.</item>
                        <item>3. Prudently.</item>
                        <item>4. Meekly.</item>
                        <item>5. Boldly.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:57120:53"/>
                     <p n="1">
                        <label>1. Seaſonably.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>Reproof is an affirmative Duty, that binds all, (though not all <note place="margin">Semper non ad ſemper.</note> alike) but not always, for every time ſin is committed, is not a fit time to reprove it, therefore you muſt chuſe a fit ſeaſon for it.</p>
                     <p>The beſt time to ſtrike the Iron is when it is hot and pliant; to Plough, when the Earth is made ſoft by Rain; and the beſt time to reprove ſin, is, when the mind of <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 36.</note> the ſinner is prepared to receive it.</p>
                     <p>There is a time to keep ſilence, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3. 7.</note> as well as to ſpeak.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <label>2. Speedily.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take no ſeaſon that is not fit for Reproof, nor neglect any that is; for either the perſon to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 13.</note> may be out of your reach, and then it will be impoſſible, or more hardened in ſin, (for the habit of ſin is intended and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by cuſtom) and then it will be more difficult to reclaim him.</p>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:57120:53"/>
                     <p>The longer any are the Devils Captives, the ſtronger are the Chains he binds them with.</p>
                     <p n="3">
                        <label>3. Prudently.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>All perſons are not alike, nor are all ſins neither, nor muſt they be reprov'd alike; you muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſult, not onely the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of time and place, but the Nature of the ſin, and both the quality and temper of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that your reproof may be receiv'd, not as an affront, but as a kindneſs to him.</p>
                     <p>Nettles and Thorns muſt be <note place="margin">Ezek. 2. 16.</note> handled in a different manner.</p>
                     <p n="4">
                        <label>4. Meekly.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>If Hatred beget Reproof, and Paſſion bring it forth, or if Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof be leavened with it, it loſes its Nature, (for it is not reproof, but railing) and will miſs of its end; for Paſſion is a ſhort Mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and one Mad man is never like to do good to another; you muſt therefore do it, not in wrath, but with a Spirit of Meekneſs,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57120:54"/> that thoſe you reprove may not be the more confirm'd in their ſin, or reſolv'd for it, but reclaim'd from it.</p>
                     <p>The bluſtering Wind makes the Traveller hold his Coat the faſter.</p>
                     <p n="5">
                        <label>5. Boldly.</label>
                     </p>
                     <p>Meekly, that the Perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd may not be offended, and boldly, that God may not be diſhonoured; meekly, that your Anger may appear not againſt him, but his ſin; and blodly, that your Zeal may appear for God.</p>
                     <p>It is a ſinful Modeſty to be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther afraid, or aſham'd to reprove ſin, and a fooliſh pity, to let any periſh in it through a fear of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing them.</p>
                     <p>My Prayer for you, ſhall be <note place="margin">Ab occultis meis pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis &amp; alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis meis, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera me Domine. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> that of St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> for himſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> that you may be kept from your own ſins, and from the ſins of others.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:57120:54"/>
                  <head>Of ſins of Omiſſion.</head>
                  <p>Sins of Omiſſion are the firſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 14. 1. Rom. 1. 21, 24. 2 Theſ. 2. 10, 11.</note> inlets to ſin; for the omiſſion of good, is the ground of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of evil.</p>
                  <p>A ſin of Omiſſion is either not doing what is Commanded, or not doing it as it is Commanded.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Not doing what is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
                  <p>Every Affirmative Command has ſomething Negative in it; and every Negative Command has ſomething Affirmative in it; that Command which enjoyns Honour and Service to God, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids whatever may tend to his Diſhonour; and that which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids the taking away the Life of any, does alſo Command an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour (ſo far as is poſſible) to preſerve that Life, and a neglect, is a ſin, becauſe a breach of that Law.</p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:57120:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:57120:55"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:57120:56"/>
                  <p>They that live not Godly, as <note place="margin">Titus 2. 12. Eph. 4. 25. 1 Pet. 2. 11, 12. Rom. 8. 1. Pſal. 34. 14.</note> well as deny Ungodlineſs; that ſpeak not truth, as well as put away lying; that walk not after the Spirit, as well as not after the Fleſh; and do not good, as well as depart from evil, are guilty of a breach of the Law, for it Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands both.</p>
                  <p>It is a ſin to do what is forbid, <note place="margin">Aequè pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat, qui omittit fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciends, &amp; facit omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenda.</note> and ſo it is alſo, not to do what is commanded; and therefore, they ſin, that do not what they ſhould, as they, that do what they ſhould not.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Not doing in a right man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner what is Commanded.</p>
                  <p>God Commands both, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors all Obedience, that is not formally, as well as materially good, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo as to the manner, as well as to the matter of it.</p>
                  <p>They are Curſed, that do not <note place="margin">Jer. 48. 10.</note> the work of the Lord; and ſo are they too, that do it negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently.</p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:57120:56"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſays of <hi>Galba,</hi> that he <note place="margin">Quod ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis erat ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra vitia, quàm cum virtutibus. Minus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſi.</note> had rather no Vice, than any Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: And <hi>Salvian</hi> ſays, that many in his time, thought themſelves therefore good, becauſe not ſo bad as others: And too many there are, that think they are therefore good, becauſe they do no evil; Saints, becauſe not Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; but how much they, or you are miſtaken by thinking ſo, will appear, by conſidering</p>
                  <p>That Sins of Omiſſion, as well as of Commiſſion, will</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Denominate you to be evil.</item>
                     <item>2. Will bring evil upon you.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. They denominate you to be evil.</p>
                  <p>A Garden is bad, if it has not good Flowers, as well as no Weeds; a Tree, if it does not bear good Fruit, as well as not bad; a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, if he does not preſerve his Maſters Goods, as well as not waſte them; and ſo are all that profeſs Religion, that appear not for it, as well as not againſt it.</p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:57120:57"/>
                  <p>Unrighteouſneſs left, is not <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 17, 18.</note> Righteouſneſs learnt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, unleſs you become Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as well as forſake Unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; and do good, as well as ceaſe to do evil, you are not good at all.</p>
                  <p>Unſavoury Salt (in this ſenſe) is no better than Poyſon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That Sins of Omiſſion will bring evil upon you.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> were Baniſh'd from the Congregation of the Lord to their tenth Generation, <note place="margin">Deut. 23. 3, 4.</note> for a Sin of Omiſſion, <hi>(viz.</hi> for not meeting the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with Bread and Water in their way out of <hi>Egypt.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Meroz</hi> was Curſed for this ſin, <note place="margin">Judges 5. 23.</note> (he, for not helping the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mighty, as well as they that helped the Mighty againſt the Lord.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his Kingdom for this Sin, <hi>(viz.</hi> for not killing <hi>Agag)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 9, 23.</note> the Fig-tree in the Vineyard was doom'd to be cut down for this
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57120:57"/> ſin, <hi>(viz.</hi> not for bearing Crabs, <note place="margin">Luke 13. 7, 8.</note> but for not bearing Figs;) the fooliſh Virgins were ſhut out of <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 3, 8.</note> Heaven for this ſin, <hi>(viz.</hi> not for waſting their Oyl, but for not getting Oyl in their Veſſels.)</p>
                  <p>The Invited Gueſt to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage-Supper, <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 11, 12, 13.</note> was caſt into outer Darkneſs for this ſin, (it was not for coming in Raggs, but for coming without a Wedding-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.)</p>
                  <p>The unprofitable Servant was <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 30.</note> caſt into outer Darkneſs for this ſin, (it was not for being Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, but for being unprofitable; it was not for waſting his Talent, but for not uſing it; nor for not having five Talents, but for not improving that one he had.)</p>
                  <p>The Rich Man was Tormented in Hell for this ſin, (it was not <note place="margin">Luke 16. 19, 20, 21, 25.</note> for being unjuſt, but for being uncharitable; it was not for hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but for not relieving him:) The great Curſe of the Goſpel <hi>(Anathema Maranatha)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 22.</note>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:57120:58"/> greater than any of the Law, is entail'd on this ſin, <hi>(viz.</hi> for not loving of Chriſt.)</p>
                  <p>Preſent Condemnation is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd againſt this ſin, <hi>(he that</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>believeth not, is condemned already)</hi> and the fatal Sentence (never to <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 41, 42.</note> be repeal'd) will at laſt be paſt againſt it, <hi>viz.</hi> not for ſtarving, ſtripping, or impriſoning Chriſts Members (though thoſe will be puniſhed as great ſins at that day) but for not Viſiting, Clothing, and Feeding them.</p>
                  <p>There are no Neuters in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and therefore, if you are not for Chriſt, you are againſt him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of little ſins, and of Cuſtom in ſin.</head>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Of little ſins.</head>
                     <p>ALL ſins (objectively conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) are alike, for they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God, who is infinite
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57120:58"/> in Power and Goodneſs; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as to their Circumſtances, they are not; for Circumſtances put a ſenſible difference into one and the ſame action, and ſin, and the aggravation of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is the aggravation of the ſin.</p>
                     <p>Some think every ſin little (but it is the greatneſs of their ſin to do ſo) and ſome think little ſins none, but they are; for,</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Little ſins are tranſgreſſions of Gods Law.</item>
                        <item>2. Little ſins are Mortal.</item>
                        <item>3. Little ſins make way for greater.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="1">1. Little ſins are tranſgreſſions <note place="margin">1 John 3. 4.</note> of Gods Law.</p>
                     <p>Thoughts are free from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <note place="margin">Cogitationis paenas nemo luit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; de minimis non curas lex.</note> of Humane Laws, and ſmall offences are little regarded, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of; but the Divine Law reaches to the leaſt ſins, and forbids the whole Latitude of ſin, from the beginning, to the end, from thoughts, to deeds, and from
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:57120:59"/> the appearance, to the act; for <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5. 22. Mat. 5. 28. Heb. 4. 12.</note> Gods Law (as the Exchequer Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts) reaches to the leaſt ſums and farthings.</p>
                     <p>Little ſpots as well as great ones made a Leproſie, as much crookedneſs may be in a ſmall line as in a greater, and as much contempt of God and his Law, in the leaſt ſin, as in the greateſt.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Little ſins are Mortal.</p>
                     <p>The breach of every Law of Earthly Kings is not Capital and Mortal, but all of the King of Heavens are; for the wages of ſin, the tranſgreſſion of thoſe Laws, <hi>(viz.</hi> of ſin indefinitely) is Death; they are not all alike great, but all are Mortal, and will <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note> (without Repentance) bring ſure Damnation, though not equal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of it; for, as the promiſe is annexed to the leaſt Grace, ſo a curſe is to the leaſt ſin.</p>
                     <p>A little leak unſtopt will ſink a Ship; a little Sword will kill as ſurely as a great one, a little Debt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57120:59"/> will caſt into Priſon as well as a great one, and a little ſin unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, will as ſurely ſend you to Hell as a greater; and when once there, it will be but ſorry comfort to think what you are there for, whether for great ſins, or ſmall ones.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Little ſins make way for greater.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>David</hi> by being Idle, became wanton, and from a wanton glance of his Eye, he proceeded to Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery; from luſt, to act, and from one act to another, <hi>viz.</hi> from Adultery, to Murder.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Solomon,</hi> from ſenſual Luſts went on to Spiritual <hi>(viz.</hi> to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry:) <hi>Judas,</hi> from Covetouſneſs, to Murder, (firſt, he grudg'd the coſtly Oyntment beſtow'd on Chriſt, and then betray'd him) and <hi>Peter,</hi> from Lying, to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; and ſo will all, not only Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, but all that indulge any ſin, wax worſe and worſe, and <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 13. Jer. 9. 3.</note> proceed from evil to evil, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <pb n="100" facs="tcp:57120:60"/> both as to kind and degree.</p>
                     <p>Little Wedges make way for greater, little Burthens ſtrengthen for greater, little Coals kindle greater, the loweſt ſtair helps up <note place="margin">Principis obſta.</note> to the higheſt, the leaſt figure in Arithmetick increaſeth the Sum, <note place="margin">In minimo eſſe fidelem, magnum eſt. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                        </note> and in the leaſt ſin there is a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency to the greateſt; it is of an increaſing Nature, and will, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs timely prevented, proceed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it is out of meaſure ſinful.</p>
                     <p>That ſin is ever moſt dangerous, that is moſt contemptible.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>Of Cuſtom in Sin.</head>
                     <p>Much might be ſaid as to the evil of Cuſtom in ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> that it will indiſpoſe you to any thing <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>. Philo</note> that is good, and diſenable all the Faculties of your Soul to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it; that it will put you upon ſinning with freedom, facility, pleaſure, and delight, and bring you under a fatal neceſſity of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whether you will or no, or
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57120:60"/> at leaſt without any ſenſe of it, like the People of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> who did not mind their Earthquakes, becauſe <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, Omne peccatum vileſcit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine &amp; fit quaſi nulium qui ad oſtia Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i vivunt nimium audien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, nihil audiunt, ex voluntate perversâ fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta eſt libido, dum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidini ſervitur, facta eſt conſuetudo, &amp; dum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudini non reſiſtitur, facta eſt neceſſitas.</note> they were daily: Or like them that lived at the Cataracts of <hi>Nilus,</hi> who by hearing too much, heard nothing at all. A doleful Paradox, but true.</p>
                     <p>But all that I ſhall ſay relating to it, ſhall be onely two things, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. That nothing provokes God more than Cuſtom in ſin.</item>
                        <item>2. That nothing is more hardly remov'd than Cuſtom in ſin.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="1">1. That nothing provokes God more than Cuſtom in ſin.</p>
                     <p>Cuſtom in ſin, is ſin by Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, (for, it is not got by one act, but by many) and the multiplication of ſin, is the great aggravation of it; the breach of Humane Laws is not leſſened, but aggravated, by a frequent repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:57120:61"/> of it, and ſo is the breach of Divine Laws too; for, as ſin has a Power, and a Law, by which (in ſome) it reigns, ſo it is the more heinous when it is ſo, for the leaſt ſin that reigns is more diſpleaſing to God, than the <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 12, 16.</note> greateſt that does not.</p>
                     <p>All Acts, whether good or bad, pleaſe or diſpleaſe, as the good or evil habits are, from whence they come.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That nothing is more hardly remov'd than Cuſtom in ſin.</p>
                     <p>Evil Habits, as well as good, are got by degrees, and perfected by uſe, (for Acts ſtrengthen Habits) and <note place="margin">A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>io perfecta non reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitur niſi imperfecté pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mó. Ab imperfecto ad perfectum conſuetudinem vincere, dura pugna.</note> the ſtronger they are, with the greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty will they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd, and overcome.</p>
                     <p>Trees well Rooted, and of ſome ſtanding, are not eaſily tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted; ſtreams of Water of long continuance, are not eaſily diverted from their Chanel; the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57120:61"/> League of Friendſhip betwixt Old Friends, is not eaſily broken; nor ſin eaſily remov'd, when habitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Cuſtom, for Cuſtom is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Nature, and that is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty (if at all) repell'd. <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Naturam expollas furcâ licet uſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currit.</hi> Mark 9. 17, 21, 26.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Devil that poſſeſs'd the Young Man from a Child, was (of all) with the greateſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty caſt out.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Cretians,</hi> when they Curſe one another, ſay, the Devil lead you into an evil Cuſtom; but my Prayer for you ſhall be, that God would keep you from it, that you may not be hardened in ſin. <note place="margin">Zech. 7. 12. <hi>Adamas né ferro qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cedit, nullis ſeil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pris, nullis malleis doma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ilis.</hi> Mark 6. 52. &amp; 16. 14.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſtone of the Heart is in all by Nature, and felt by all that are not dead in ſin; your Heart by Nature is a ſtone, and by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in ſin it will be as an Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, the hardeſt (as Naturaliſts obſerve) of all ſtones; a greater Miſery than which you cannot lye under, either here, or in Hell; for Hell it ſelf would be no Hell to any of a tender and broken Heart.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57120:62"/>
                  <head>Of Thoughts.</head>
                  <p>The great Miſery come upon all by reaſon of ſin, is, that every <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 5.</note> imagination of the thoughts of their Heart are evil, onely evil, and continually ſo.</p>
                  <p>Evil thoughts are all thoughts of evil againſt God and Man, ſo called, either as ariſing from evil, or tending to it.</p>
                  <p>Thoughts are known to God. <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 16.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Ark that was made cloſe on every ſide, had a Window on the top towards Heaven, as an Emblem of Gods Omniſcience, who ſees you, not onely when in ſecret, but the ſecret within you, for he knows your thoughts (yea your thought, every ſingle thought) afar off, <hi>viz.</hi> either <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 2. Ezek. 11. 5.</note> what they will be, before you think them, or what they were, when you have forgotten them.</p>
                  <p>They are reſerv'd Caſes known to him onely, nor can he forget
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:57120:62"/> them, for he requires that which <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3. 15.</note> is paſt.</p>
                  <p>Thoughts ſhall be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Judgment.</p>
                  <p>Thoughts (as well as words and actions) are written in Gods Book, and ſhall be made known, <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. <hi>ult.</hi> Rom. 2. 16. 1 Cor. 4. 5.</note> when the ſecrets of Men ſhall be judged, the counſel of the Heart made manifeſt, and the hidden things of Darkneſs brought into light.</p>
                  <p>And many whoſe underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings ſpoke them Men, and their words Chriſtians, when on Earth, ſhall be found (at that day) by their thoughts, to have been worſe than Beaſts.</p>
                  <p>Evil thoughts are ſins, and tranſgreſſions of Gods Law.</p>
                  <p>The Laws of Men reach but to words and Actions, but Gods <note place="margin">Heb. 4. 12. Prov. 6. 18. &amp; 15. 26. Prov. 24. 9.</note> Law reaches to thoughts, and forbids, not onely evil words and deeds, but all evil thoughts tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them. The thoughts of Fooliſhneſs is ſin, and therefore,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57120:63"/> unleſs you be cleanſed from them, <note place="margin">Jer. 4. 14.</note> you cannot be ſaved.</p>
                  <p>A dumb Man may be damn'd for the ſins of his thoughts.</p>
                  <p>There may be ſin in the thoughts, inward motions to it, though no outward acts of it; yea, ſin may be reiterated there, when the acts of it ceaſe; and as much ſin may be in the thoughts in a day, as would take up the actions of a whole Life to compleat and finiſh: There are many ways by which Men can reſtrain or puniſh the acts of ſin, but none either to reſtrain or puniſh the thoughts of it; ſinful actions are publick and open Offences, ſinful thoughts are more inward and ſecret, they as the uncleanneſs of <hi>Abſalom</hi> with <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 22.</note> his Father's Concubines in the face of the Sun and the ſight of all <hi>Iſrael;</hi> theſe, as the Idolatry of the Ancients of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> in the dark, in the Chambers of their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery; <note place="margin">Ezek. 8. 12.</note> they, the Luſts of the fleſh, theſe, Spiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes;
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:57120:63"/> they defile the Body, theſe more immediately defile the Soul, the ſeat of the Spirit; they, may caſt you out of the favour of good Men, but theſe will hinder your Communion with God; for,</p>
                  <p>Communion with God in a way of Duty, is had by thoughts more than by words.</p>
                  <p>Evil thoughts make way for evil actions.</p>
                  <p>The two firſt ſins committed by the Angels and <hi>Adam,</hi> began in the thoughts, (an averſion of their will from God) and they are ſtill the Seed of Sin, (firſt, evil Thoughts, and then Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Adulteries, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if you would prevent the acts of ſin, you muſt put a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon your thoughts.</p>
                  <p>The heavieſt Chains are put upon the vileſt Malefactors.</p>
                  <p>Here ſins Leproſie at firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, and as the Leproſie, when it took but a thread of a woollen, or linnen Garment, ſoon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:57120:64"/> the whole; ſo theſe, if not timely prevented, will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence the whole actions of your Life, and make them evil. Now, that they may not,</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) You muſt ſet a ſtrict watch over your Heart.</p>
                  <p>Thoughts are the inward mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <note place="margin">Proles ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</note> and innumerable Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heart, proceeding as Naturally from it, as beams from the Sun, and ſtreams from a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; <note place="margin">Jer. 17. 9.</note> the Heart is deſperately wicked, the ſink of all Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">Pſal. 41. 6.</note> it gathers Iniquity to it ſelf (as an old Sore in the Body draws <note place="margin">Prov. 4. 23.</note> all the ill humours to it,) and ſends it abroad upon all occaſions; and therefore you muſt keep it with all diligence, that it may not; you muſt keep the outward Senſes (ſhut thoſe Windows, <note place="margin">Claude quinque fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtras, &amp; tota lucebit domus. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rab. Prov.</hi>
                     </note> that no unclean Birds may enter in) but above all, your Heart, for out of it proceed evil thoughts.</p>
                  <p>The Fountain muſt be kept pure and clean, or elſe the ſtreams will not be ſo.</p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:57120:64"/>
                  <p n="2">(2.) Let your thoughts be <note place="margin">Phil. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> well employ'd: Think on the things that are true, and caſt out all thoughts of a Lie, and Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, think on the things that <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> are Honeſt and Venerable, and abhor all Vanity and Frothineſs of Spirit; think on the things that are juſt, and let not a thought of fraud, or deceit lodge within you; think on the things that are pure, and away with what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is immodeſt; think on the things that are lovely, and hate <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> all peeviſhneſs and frowardneſs of Spirit; think on things of good Report, and entertain not a thought of any thing that may tend to your diſhonour.</p>
                  <p>Idleneſs is Fewel to vitious thoughts, and therefore, as it is an axiom in State, to ſet active Spirits on work, that they may do no miſchief; ſo here, you muſt employ your thoughts about No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Arguments, and Bleſſed Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, if you would have them
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57120:65"/> (like the Heavenly Bodies) to move orderly, and become, not foundations of diſturbance, but helps to Piety.</p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) Beg Gods aſſiſtance in all.</p>
                  <p>God has the greateſt Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your thoughts (they are too many, and too ſtrong for you to rule) and therefore, commit your works to him, that your <note place="margin">Prov. 16. 3.</note> thoughts may be eſtabliſhed, or when they become diſorderly, and irregular, cry out unto him, as <hi>Auſtin</hi> did, againſt ſinful thoughts, in the words of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Save me, O God, for the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 69. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>waters are come in unto my Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And there is good reaſon for it, for, ſuch as your thoughts are, ſuch are you in Gods eſteem.</p>
                  <p>We judge of Mens thoughts by their words and actions, but God judges of the words and actions of all, by their thoughts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:57120:65"/>
                  <head>Of Evil Company.</head>
                  <p>Man is a ſociable Creature, and will not be without Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> good or bad; but they that are wiſe, will avoid as much as they can the ſociety of them that are evil; and how much it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you ſo to do, will appear, if you conſider, that,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Evil Company will ſhew what you are.</item>
                     <item>2. Evil Company will make you what you ſhould not be.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Evil Company will ſhew what you are.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> judg'd of the diſpoſition of their Children by their Company; and <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> of his two Daughters, <hi>(Livia</hi> and <hi>Julia)</hi> when he ſaw grave Senators converſing with one, and wanton Perſons with <note place="margin">Noſcitur ex ſocio, qui non cognoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur ex ſe.</note> the other; and ſo will the World of yours, for none can be ſo well known by themſelves, as by their
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57120:66"/> Company. The Fowls of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven flock together, and the Beaſts on Earth herd together, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their kind, and ſo do wicked men (the greater Beaſts of the two) like <hi>Flora,</hi> who ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd with ill-favour'd Women like her ſelf; and if you are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently found among them that <note place="margin">Inter diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares mores quae poteſt eſſe amici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia?</note> are evil, or are too intimate with them, you will be look'd upon as one of them.</p>
                  <p>They are none of Gods Friends, that converſe familiarly with his Enemies.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Evil Company will make you what you ſhould not be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dinah</hi> (the Daughter of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 1, 2.</note> went gadding abroad to ſee the Maids of the Countrey, till ſhe was none her ſelf. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 42. 15.</note> by being in <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Court, learn'd to ſwear by the Life of <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> though <note place="margin">Homo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus telum diaboli.</note> they hated the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> yet by living among them, they learned their Manners, their Luſts, not
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57120:66"/> their Laws; (they that ſhould have Converted them, were, as one ſays, perverted by them, and became twice their Slaves, their Bodies being Conquered by their Weapons, and their Souls by their Vices.) <hi>Solomon,</hi> by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing <note place="margin">Neh. 13. 26.</note> with Idolatrous Women, became Idolatrous: <hi>Peter,</hi> whileſt he warm'd himſelf at the fire in <note place="margin">Luke 22. 55, 56, 57. <hi>Faſcinus unius, mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum peſtis.</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian.</note> the High Prieſts Hall, got cold, and abated in his Zeal; he warm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Hands, but cooled his Heart. Evil Company (among other things, as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) helped on to make the Younger Brother a Prodigal:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. His Portion.</item>
                     <item>2. His Fathers Indulgence.</item>
                     <item>3. His Youth.</item>
                     <item>4. Evil Company.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> (as he confeſſes) committed ſome ſins, which he had not before, to gain Credit and Eſteem with his Companions; and there is no good Man (as <hi>Epictetus</hi> ſays) but will either
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:57120:67"/> ſuffer evil, or learn it from them that are evil.</p>
                  <p>Pure Streams paſſing by a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt <note place="margin">Inficitur terrae ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus unda fluens. Aliquod malum, propter vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> Soil, contract ſome of its filth; ruſty Metals corrupt the pure, ſcabby Sheep, rotten Grapes, and ſore Eyes, will infect the ſound; and evil Men the good, by converſing with them: It is ſeldom found, that the bad are made better by it, but the good made worſe, getting a bane (with <hi>Peter)</hi> where they could not get a bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>It is odds to be with the Lame, and not to learn to limp.</p>
                  <p>It is true, ſometimes good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples put others upon the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of that which is good; when <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid he would not leave <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 35.</note> Chriſt, all the Diſciples ſaid ſo too; and <hi>Veſpatian</hi>'s Frugality gave check to the <hi>Romans</hi> Luxury; but they oftner lead to that which is evil, <hi>(Nero</hi>'s Fiddle had too many Dancers after it) for all Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are prone to be led more by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57120:67"/> Example than Precept, and by bad Examples more than good ones; living, not as they ſhould, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Non quo eundum, ſed quo itur, non ad ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, ſed ad ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem,</hi> Seneca <hi>de vitâ beatâ.</hi> Pſal. 119. 115. Prov. 4. 14. Iſa. 6. 5. 1 Pet. 4. 3.</note> but as they ſee the moſt do, and (as beaſts) following the drove, or herd, though it be to their own deſtruction; and therefore, if you would neither be, nor do, as they, delight not to be where they are; or when Charity or Neceſſity may oblige you to it, be ſeparated from their ſins, when you are not from their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and at all times ſhun and avoid the works of Iniquity, <note place="margin">Eph. 5. 11.</note> though ſometimes you cannot the workers of it.</p>
                  <p>Their Hatred is better than <note place="margin">Non eſt perfecté bonus, niſi qui cum malus bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> their Company.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of the Spirit.</head>
                  <p>The Spirit is ſometimes taken for the whole Divine Nature, and equally agrees with any Perſon of the Godhead, when abſtractedly conſidered.</p>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:57120:68"/>
                  <p>Sometimes for the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 14. 1 Pet. 3. 18.</note> of Chriſt; for as fleſh is ſometimes taken for his Humane Nature, ſo Spirit is for his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature.</p>
                  <p>Sometimes for the Holy Ghoſt (as diſtinct from the Father and <note place="margin">1 John 5. 7.</note> the Son) with all its Gifts and Graces, who Sanctifies, Teaches, Quickens, Guides, and Comforts all in whom he dwells; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it concerns you,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. To ask God for this Spirit.</item>
                     <item>2. To do nothing (when given) to grieve it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Enquire of your ſelf, as <hi>Paul</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts 19. 2.</note> did of the Diſciples at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> whether as yet you have receiv'd the Holy Spirit, (with its Gifts and Graces) and if upon enquiry you find you have not, then,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Ask God for it.</item>
                     <item>2. Do nothing, when given, to grieve it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Ask God for the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>God promiſed at firſt, that he <note place="margin">Joel 2. 28.</note> would pour out his Spirit upon
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:57120:68"/> all fleſh, <hi>viz.</hi> extenſively, and <note place="margin">Iſa. 30. 19. &amp; 44. 3: &amp; 49. 15. &amp; 55. 1. &amp; 59. 21. &amp; 65. 24. Rom. 10. 12. Eph. 3. 20. Tit. 3 6. James 1 5.</note> intenſively; not upon the <hi>Jews</hi> onely (to whom it was then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd) but upon all; and more of that Spirit than formerly was poured out upon them, and ſince that, he has promiſed to give his Spirit to them that ask it; and as an encouragement to asking, has aſſured, that he will much more <note place="margin">Luke 11. 13.</note> give it, than Earthly Parents ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can or will give good Gifts to their Children.</p>
                  <p>They are Earthly, but God is Heavenly; they Fathers of the Fleſh, he of the Spirit; they evil <hi>(viz.</hi> either ſimply, or compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively) but he infinitely good; a more Rich, Bountiful, Faithful, <note place="margin">Cujus p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipatione ſumus juſti, ejus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratione ſumus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſti.</note> and a more tender hearted Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than any of them; and therefore, both can, and will much more willingly, freely, certainly, compaſſionately, abundantly, and conſtantly give (than they) the Spirit to all that ask him for it.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:57120:69"/>
                  <p>Since then God is ſo willing to give his Spirit, be you earneſt and importunate for it; there is good reaſon you ſhould, for it had been better you had never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 9</note> the Spirit of a Man, unleſs you have this Spirit of God.</p>
                  <p>And that you may ſpeed in asking, ſeek it in Chriſts Name, <note place="margin">Joh. 1. 16. &amp; 3. 34.</note> who received the Spirit without meaſure for you, and meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly fulfills the promiſe of it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Do nothing to grieve the Spirit, when given to you:</p>
                  <p>There is mention made (in Scripture) of reſiſting, quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <note place="margin">Acts 7. 51. 1 Theſ. 5. 19. Eph. 4. 30.</note> and grieving the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, (as uſually ſaid) is proper to Impenitents, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to Apoſtates, and the third to Saints.</p>
                  <p>Properly, the Spirit cannot be grieved (it being contrary to the <note place="margin">Per figuram non natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. Quoad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum, non quoad af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum.</note> Nature of the Spirit, either to make any ſad, or it ſelf to be made ſo,) but Metaphorically it may; and then it is, when it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57120:69"/> as one grieved, and then you may be ſaid to do it, when you do thoſe things that would grieve the Spirit, if the Spirit was capable of it; and this two ways, <hi>viz.</hi> either by ſins of Omiſſion, or of Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By ſins of Omiſſion, or by neglecting the good you ſhould do, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By idleneſs and ſlothfulneſs, by not anſwering to the calls, and not yielding to the motions of the Spirit, by not walking in the light and ſtrength, in the fellowſhip and communion, in the exerciſe of the Graces, and <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 1.</note> in the comforts of the Spirit; for it is a ſin to oppoſe the Comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well as the Sanctifying work of the Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By ſins of Commiſſion, or by doing that which you ſhould not, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By violating of Truth in any kind (whether Natural or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral) by inordinate love to the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:57120:70"/> World (prizing Carnal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort above Spiritual) by impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of thoughts (which defile the Soul, the place of the Spirits Reſidence) by cauſeleſs doubts and fears, deſpondency under troubles (both inward and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward) in conſtancy, and in ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in Religion; or deadneſs, formality, and Spiritual Pride in the Duties of it.</p>
                  <p>They are all (one way or ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) againſt the Spirit, either as a Governour, Guide, Witneſs, or Comforter, and as ſuch, they grieve it; for by them its Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſlighted, its Aſſiſtances are rejected, its Influences perverted, or its Comforts diſ-eſteem'd, and counted ſmall; and therefore it concerns you to beware of them, and the more, in that,</p>
                  <p>By thus grieving the good Spirit, you will pleaſe the Devil the evil Spirit; and by grieving the one, and pleaſing the other, you will grieve and diſpleaſe your
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57120:70"/> own Spirit at laſt, for grieving makes way for quenching, and by quenching the Spirit, you may in time be left to commit that great tranſgreſſion, the unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable ſin againſt it.</p>
                  <p>All ſins grieve the Spirit, but thoſe that grieve the ſinner.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Self-examination.</head>
                  <p>Examination is the Judicial proceeding of a ſinner with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or the act of Conſcience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, comparing all his actions with the Rule, and accordingly paſſing ſentence either of Abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Condemnation; for, or againſt himſelf.</p>
                  <p>The Command makes it a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5. Gal. 6. 3, 4. <hi>Si ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>aper hoc quum op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſemter facus.</hi> Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard <hi>in Cant. 58. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m.</hi>
                     </note> and the neglect of it, a Sin.</p>
                  <p>A Duty at all times, but more eſpecially at ſome times.</p>
                  <p>A difficult Duty.</p>
                  <p>Reflex acts are (by Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers) counted moſt difficult; and this, of all the Duties of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:57120:71"/> Chriſtianity, is none of the leaſt that is ſo.</p>
                  <p>Yet muſt not be omitted; for they that will do nothing that is difficult in Religion, have no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
                  <p>The Perſons concern'd in it, are <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 28. A Man, <hi>i. e.</hi> every man, ſo the Old Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reads it, and ſo <hi>Beza</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlates it. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>quiſquis,</hi> Eraſmus.</note> not a few onely, or many, but all; all, either as Communicants, or Chriſtians, both real and nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; for none are too good, or too great for it.</p>
                  <p>It belongs but to few to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine others, but it concerns all to examine themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The things to which it relates, are almoſt infinite, <hi>viz.</hi> every thing, thought, ſpoken, and done, whether good or evil.</p>
                  <p>Examination is as a petty Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to prevent (or the better to prepare for) a General Aſſize; Mans Judgment to anticipate Gods, and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 31.</note> therefore muſt carry a proportion to it.</p>
                  <p>God will judge every thing <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 14.</note> (Morally good and evil) then,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:57120:71"/> and ſo muſt every one now.</p>
                  <p>The Rule by which it is to be guided is the Word of God.</p>
                  <p>It is not he that others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend, that is approved (for, they <note place="margin">2 Cor. 10. 18.</note> may think better of him than he is) nor he that commendeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (for he may be better than others, and better than he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has formerly been, and yet <note place="margin">Luke 18. 11.</note> not good, or at leaſt, not ſo good as he ſhould be) but he whom God commendeth, that is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; and therefore none muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelf by anothers good Opinion of him, nor by his own good Opinion of himſelf, (for both may be miſtaken) but by the Word of God, by which onely the regularity, or irregularity of his actions will appear, God will hereafter judge you by it; and therefore, the beſt courſe you can take, is to judge your ſelf by it <note place="margin">Rectum eſt index ſui, &amp; ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iqui.</note> now; and that you may, you muſt get a clear and right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it.</p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:57120:72"/>
                  <p>By this light you will ſee light, but unleſs you have Eyes to ſee it, it will be of no more Advantage to you, than the light of the Sun to them that are blind, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee. A juſt Judge deſires a clear Evidence, a good Cauſe, a fair Tryal, an upright Heart, a ſearch; and the better any are, the more willing they will be to know the worſt of themſelves; not to do it, may add ſomething to your ſecurity, but nothing to your ſafety: Therefore,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Be exact in the examination of your ſelf.</item>
                     <item>2. Beg Gods Examination up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. Be exact in the examination <note place="margin">Tecum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ua.</note> of your ſelf.</p>
                  <p>It muſt not be ſuperficial and ſlight, remiſs and careleſs, but ſtrict and exact, ſearching every corner of your Heart, and cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring every irregularity of your Life; ſeeking, that you may find what is amiſs, and untill you do;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57120:72"/> and with good reaſon, for, as they are the worſt ſort of Cheats, that deceive themſelves, ſo they are the worſt of that ſort, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves in the concerns of their Soul.</p>
                  <p>It is far more ſafe to condemn than to acquit your ſelf without cauſe. For by one, your Peace will be loſt for a time onely, but by the other, your Soul will be loſt for ever.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beg Gods examination upon yours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rachel</hi> was willing to have any <note place="margin">Gen. 31. 34, 35.</note> place ſearched for the Idols (ſhe had ſtole from <hi>Laban)</hi> but that on which ſhe ſat to cover them; and a Thief may be content, that a blind Man that cannot ſee, or his fellow Thief, that will not, ſhould ſearch his Houſe; and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites reſt ſatisfied with their own Examination, or of thoſe like themſelves; but they that are ſincere, and upright, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that any ſhould examine
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57120:73"/> them; yea (with <hi>David)</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that God ſhould do it, and that truth ſhould take place, though againſt themſelves.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>David</hi> had examined <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 23, 24.</note> himſelf, he appealed to God, not as to one that he would have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with his own Opinion of himſelf, nor with the Opinion of others concerning him, but as to one that was the ſearcher of Hearts, and that he himſelf would be ſearched by; he did not deſire that his Life onely, but his Heart (the moſt ſuſpected place) might be ſearch'd, and that not ſuperficially, but through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that the matter might be fully travers'd, and paſs through all Courts of Tryal, as appears by the multiplying of words, (ſearch, know, try, and ſee) and by the extent of it, <hi>viz.</hi> that not one thought, or way onely, but that all his ways and thoughts might be enquir'd into; and that if there was any ſin that he did
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:57120:73"/> not ſee, or could not, it might be done away.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, when you have done all that you can in it, deſire God to examine you and your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination too; and that if there be any ſin in you, that either you do not ſee, or cannot, that he would ſhew it to you; or if there be any ſin that you would not ſee, that he would do away that ſin, and the Hypocriſie that would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge it.</p>
                  <p>It is onely by the light of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that you can ſee the Hell that is within you.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Watchfulneſs.</head>
                  <p>Watchfulneſs is a Duty that concerns all <hi>(I ſay unto all, watch)</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mark 13. 37.</note> it is your Duty, and ought to be matter of your great care, in that,</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. There are Eyes upon you.</item>
                     <item>2. There are Enemies againſt you.</item>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:57120:74"/>
                     <item>3. Ruine attends you, if you do not.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. There are Eyes upon you.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>(1.) Of Men, both good and bad.</item>
                     <item>(2.) Of Angels, both good and bad.</item>
                     <item>(3.) Of Conſcience, which is Gods Deputy, and a ſtrict ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerver <note place="margin">Intimus magiſter.</note> of all your ways.</item>
                     <item>(4.) Of God, who is every where by his Power and Eſſence, and therefore Omniſcient becauſe Omnipreſent, and (like the Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Nerve) ſees all, but is ſeen of none.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Good Men obſerve, and will either be pleas'd or diſpleas'd, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, or grieve at your good and evil actions.</p>
                  <p>Evil Men obſerve, and will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reproach you for your ſins, or be hardened in their ſins by them.</p>
                  <p>Good Angels obſerve, who will miniſter to you, rejoyce over you, <note place="margin">Heb. 1. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> protect, and defend you, if you
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57120:74"/> do that which is good; or ſet againſt you, and become Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to you, if you do not.</p>
                  <p>Evil Angels obſerve, who will be as ſo many Witneſſes againſt you, your Accuſers and Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors too, if you yield to thoſe ſins that now they tempt you to.</p>
                  <p>Conſcience obſerves, either to Acquit or Condemn you.</p>
                  <p>And God obſerves, to Judge <note place="margin">Eccl. 12. <hi>ult.</hi>
                     </note> you.</p>
                  <p>Live therefore as in open view, and act as one, that has the Eyes of all upon you.</p>
                  <p>If you do not watch, you are watched.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. There are Enemies againſt you.</p>
                  <p>Of all which, the Devil and the Fleſh are the principal; for all other Enemies hurt either by his Inſtigation, or your own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt inclination.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Devil, who is ſtrong, <note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 8.</note> ſubtile, and active.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:57120:75"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Strong.</hi> A weak Enemy is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, and not much to be regarded; but this is ſtrong, not onely terrible to affright, but ſtrong to hurt.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Active.</hi> A ſloathful ſluggiſh Enemy is not much to be feared; <note place="margin">Job 1. 7.</note> but this is active and diligent; he walks his Rounds (he goes about) and is ever upon his Watch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Subtile.</hi> He prevails more by Policy than by Strength; and therefore, it concerns you, neither <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 11.</note> to be ignorant of his Devices, nor careleſs of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Fleſh, a reſtleſs and unwearied Enemy, that acts with vehemency and conſtancy, not <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 17. James 4. 5.</note> outward, but inward; an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my within you, that makes way for all the other, and the more dangerous becauſe ſo.</p>
                  <p>Since then you can be no where ſafe, unleſs watchful; be no where, nor at any time ſecure, but watch theſe watchful Enemies.</p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:57120:75"/>
                  <p n="3">3. Ruine attends you if you do not watch.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his Spear, and <hi>Samſon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 26. 7, 12. Judg. 16. 19. 1 Theſ. 5. 3.</note> his Hair, when aſleep; and your Security will be the Enemies Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity; and therefore it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns you to have all your ways (inward and outward) Rail'd in on both ſides with Watchfulneſs <note place="margin">Luke 21. 36. Rev. 4. 8.</note> and Prayer, and to have your Eyes open, to watch againſt the Corruptions from within, and the Snares from without.</p>
                  <p>The weakeſt when watchful, are more ſafe, than the ſtrongeſt when ſecure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Of Humility.</head>
                  <p>Pride is ſelf-exaltation from a <note place="margin">Superbia eſt appeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus propriae excellentiae. Humilitas eſt volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria mentis incurvatio ex Dei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitu, &amp; noſtri.</note> vain conceit of Worth and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency.</p>
                  <p>Humility is ſelf-debaſement, from a real ſenſe of vileneſs and unworthineſs.</p>
                  <p>That is the Badge of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and his followers; this of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:57120:76"/> Chriſt and his Diſciples; one of the Principles of Practical Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (as Privation is of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy) and both the Garment and Ornament of Chriſtians; and therefore, be clothed with it, and walk <note place="margin">Annibilatio animae Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale vacuum. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, It comes from a word that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a knot, and is of uſe not onely to faſten the Graces together, but to adorn alſo.</note> daily in it, with God, with others, and with your ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. With God.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) By a lowly demeanor in all your approaches to him.</p>
                  <p>The diſtance betwixt God and you is great (as great as betwixt infinite and finite) great as you are a Creature, but greater as a ſinner; and in all Duties there is matter for Humility (as well as in ſins) for when they appear brighteſt, (as the Moon when it ſhines ſo) they have their dark ſpots and imperfections; and <note place="margin">Ezra 9. 6.</note> therefore the nearer and greater your Communion with God is, the greater your Humility ſhould be,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:57120:76"/> as <hi>Archimedes</hi> his Engine, the higher it aſcended, the lower it deſcended.</p>
                  <p>All the King of Heavens Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice muſt be on the Knee; ſo that if you are proud, or not humble in it, you ſerve not God, but the Devil. <note place="margin">1 Cor 10. 31.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) By doing all to his Glory. Proud perſons think they are <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nemini debeo,</hi> The Spiders Motto. Hab. 1. 16. Hoſ. 10. 1.</note> beholden to none, and therefore Sacrifice to their own Net, and (with <hi>Ephraim)</hi> bring forth fruit to themſelves; but do you in all your actions, both Civil and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, make him your End; and in all your ways, at home, and abroad; in your Houſe as well as in his, and on your days as well as on his, do all to his Honour, that in his goodneſs and <note place="margin">Soli D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> greatneſs he may be glorified by you.</p>
                  <p>An humble ſinner is more to Gods mind, and more for his Ends and Glory, than a proud Saint.</p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:57120:77"/>
                  <p n="2">2. With others.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By not ſeeking Honour from them.</item>
                     <item>2. By not being lifted up when praiſed; nor enraged, when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam'd, or injur'd by them.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">1. By not ſeeking Honour from them.</p>
                  <p>Pride was the Angels ſin (it caſt them out of Heaven) the firſt ſin in Man, and the great ſin that appears in all by Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Commodus</hi> the Emperour would be called <hi>Hercules,</hi> and ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the People in a Lions skin, that he might be accounted King of Men, as the Lion was of Beaſts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> would have the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Jupiter</hi>'s Son, and be reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned one of the Race of the gods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Domitian</hi> would have the Title of Lord God.</p>
                  <p>Anti-Chriſt, the Man of ſin, <note place="margin">2 Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 2. 3. 4.</note> exalteth himſelf above all that is called God.</p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:57120:77"/>
                  <p>And all Men (through the Pride that is in them) Naturally ſeek Honour in the World, (as <hi>Saul</hi> did before <hi>Iſrael)</hi> and deſire <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 30. <hi>Aut</hi> Caeſar <hi>aut nullus.</hi>
                     </note> to be great, or nothing; but do not you ſeek what is greateſt, or higheſt in the eſteem of the World, but what is fitteſt and beſt for you, that you may have Honour from God, if not from Men; or be humble, and you ſhall have Honour, for Humility <note place="margin">Prov. 15. 33. Prov. 29. 23. Luke 14. 11. Gen. 14. &amp; 40, 41.</note> treads the path to it; Pride ſeeks it, but Humility finds it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that humbleth himſelf ſhall be exalted. Joſeph</hi> was firſt in the Dungeon, and then in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By not being lifted up, when praiſed; nor enraged, when de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fam'd, or injur'd by them.</p>
                  <p>Be not lift up in your ſpirit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond meaſure, if prais'd, nor en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd, if revil'd and reproach'd, but meekly receive both, as not much concern'd for either; for you cannot be too vile in your
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57120:78"/> own Eyes, nor too much humbled under it.</p>
                  <p>A Heathen, when revil'd, told the Reviler, that all he ſaid againſt him was true, and much more, and ſo he would ſay, if he knew that which he did of himſelf; and all that are truly humble, either do, or ſhould think better <note place="margin">Rom. 12. 10. Phil. 2. 3.</note> of others, than of themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. With your ſelf.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. By being content with your condition, whatever it is.</item>
                     <item>2. By having a low and mean opinion of your ſelf, under all that you poſſeſs and enjoy.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p n="1">(1.) By being content with your condition.</p>
                  <p>Some cannot live unleſs they abound, and therefore murmur and complain when they do not: Proud Beggars will have the beſt or nothing; but be you content with what you have, looking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Aliud eſt undè vivas, aliud undè ſuperbias.</note> every little thing received, as great, and every great thing, as too much.</p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:57120:78"/>
                  <p>You cannot have ſo little as you deſerve, and therefore, how low ſoever your condition is, let your mind be lower.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) By having a low and mean opinion of your ſelf, under all that you poſſeſs and enjoy.</p>
                  <p>Indeed there is nothing you can have, that can reaſonably af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford any matter for Pride.</p>
                  <p>Not Riches.</p>
                  <p>Not Silks and Furrs, the caſt Clothes of Worms and dead Beaſts; for, as they are badges of Spiritual Nakedneſs, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings of ſhame (the fruit of ſin) they afford greater matter of Humility, than Pride.</p>
                  <p>Not Gold and Silver, the more <note place="margin">Ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>idius lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um.</note> refined Dirt and Garbage of the Earth; theſe are the food of Moths and Ruſt, and therefore no food for Pride.</p>
                  <p>Not Knowledge, for <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Scio quod neſcio,</hi> Socrates. <hi>Neſciendo ſcire, &amp; ſciendo neſcire,</hi> Gregory.</note> it is but imperfect in any; the greateſt part of what you know, is the leaſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:57120:79"/> part of what you know not; and therefore you ſhould by not knowing, know; and by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not know the gift that is in you.</p>
                  <p>It will be from Ignorance of your Ignorance, if you become proud of your Knowledge.</p>
                  <p>Not Grace, for it is given to teach Humility; God gives Grace to the humble, and Grace gives Humility; and the more any have of it, the more humble they will be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moſes</hi> acknowledges that he was but duſt and aſhes, (the weakeſt and vileſt part of the Earth;) <hi>Jacob,</hi> that he was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 27. &amp; 32. 10. 1 Tim. 1. 15. 1 Cor. 15. 9. Eph. 3. 8. Mat. 11. 29. Exod. 44. 29.</note> of the leaſt of all thoſe Mercies received: <hi>Paul,</hi> that he was the greateſt of ſinners, the leaſt of the Apoſtles, and leſs than the leaſt of all Saints. Chriſt, the Lord of Glory, was meek and lowly; and the more real worth any have, the leſs they will ſee it, like <hi>Moſes,</hi> who, when his
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:57120:79"/> face did ſhine, knew it not; or the higher they are in the eſteem of others, the lower they will be in their own, as the Sun when higheſt, caſts the leaſt ſhadow, or a Taper, whileſt it gives light to others, caſts a ſhadow before its own ſtation.</p>
                  <p>A Cypher in Arithmetick, though of no worth in it ſelf, yet gives value to all that is added to it, and ſo will Humility.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Time, Death, and Judgment.</head>
               <p>I Have a Treatiſe by me of theſe, that I intend to publiſh, and therefore ſhall onely briefly give you my Advice here as to Time, Death, and Judgment.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>1. As to Time.</head>
                  <p>If you would ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how precious a thing Time is, how much it is (ſooner or later)
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:57120:80"/> prized by all; how high they are in God's eſteem, that improve their time (for they are higheſt in his eſteem, that make moſt account of his Soveraignty) how happy ſome are while living, in the Comfort they receive by it? How many, when dying, would give all the World (if they had it to give, and it would be taken) as a price to redeem the time that in Life they vainly ſpent, and trifled away? How many are tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in Hell (and will be eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally ſo) for the neglect and abuſe of it? How infinitely ſhort the whole time of Life well ſpent, will fall of the Reward that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it? How much miſpent time there is, and will be in your beſt ſpent time? How ſhort and uncertain your time is, and how ſtrict an account you muſt give of it, you would ſee great reaſon to take care that no part of it be ſpent either in ſin, or idleneſs.</p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:57120:80"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Not in ſin.</p>
                  <p>Sin is an evil of the greateſt Malignity, and all time ſpent in it, is loſt; for,</p>
                  <p>If it is not bewail'd, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, it will ruine you; and if it is, yet the time ſo ſpent is loſt, in that it might have been better employ'd, cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>called (for though Repentance will bring ſorrow for ſin, yet it can never bring back the time loſt by it) nor ever by you be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd for.</p>
                  <p>You can never give a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of a bad matter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Not in Idleneſs; for,</p>
                  <p>Idleneſs is both a ſin, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let to any, or all ſin.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It is a ſin.</p>
                  <p>Idleneſs was not allowed in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 15. Then <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor,</hi> now <hi>labor ad ſudorem.</hi>
                     </note> (for <hi>Adam</hi> was put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to work) much leſs then is it allowed in a ſtate of Degeneracy, but forbid; there are no <hi>feriae,</hi> no idle days nor hours, as one ſays, in the Kalendar
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57120:81"/> of Heaven, but as to every purpoſe there is a time, ſo to every time a purpoſe; God having appointed <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 3 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> every day and hour to be filled up with ſomething that is either work, or tends to it.</p>
                  <q>Maxima pars debitur ſtudio, minor cibo, minima ſomno, nulla otio.</q>
                  <p>And yet how many are there, who call themſelves Chriſtians, and cannot but ſay they have work to do, that trifle away their time as much as <hi>Domitian</hi> did in catching Flies, <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> in Spinning, <hi>Caligula</hi> in gathering Cockles, <hi>Nero</hi> (with his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) in picking up Pebbles; and are ſcarce ever ſo well employ'd as <hi>Protogenes,</hi> who was ſeven Years Painting a Man and his Dog.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It is an in-let to ſin.</p>
                  <p>Empty Stomacks gather Wind, ſtanding Waters putrifie, Weeds
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:57120:81"/> grow moſt in a fallow, and out of Idleneſs comes not onely no good, but all evil; for, by doing nothing, you will eaſily be led to do that which is worſe than no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt called his Diſciples <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 19. Mark 1. 16, 17. 2 Sam. 11. 2, 3, 4.</note> 
                     <hi>(James</hi> and <hi>John, Simon</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew)</hi> when buſie at their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; but the Devil will call you (as he did <hi>David)</hi> when idle, and not employ'd; and therefore be never ſo, that you may not be at leiſure to hearken to him; if you do not ſet your ſelf on work, the Devil will; and therefore at all times do it, that he at any time may not.</p>
                  <p>The rolling ſtone gathers no Moſs.</p>
                  <q>Quantò magìs occupatum Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus invenit tantò minùs occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat.</q>
                  <p>Idleneſs will render you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to God, unprofitable to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57120:82"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:57120:82"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:57120:83"/> the World, ſcandalous to them that are good, and burdenſome to your ſelf; be wiſe therefore (as the Wiſe men in <hi>Eſther)</hi> knowing your time, and get un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding <note place="margin">Eſther 1. 13. 1 Chron. 12. 32. The heads of them were two hundred, but there are few or none of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ribe (in this ſenſe) left. Rev. 10. 6.</note> (with the Children of <hi>Iſſachar)</hi> to know what you ought to do, and do it; be ever doing ſomething for your own good, or the good of others, that you may with comfort look over into Eternity, and not fear, when the Angel ſhall ſtand on the Earth and lift up his Hand, and ſwear by him that lives for ever and ever, that time ſhall be no more.</p>
                  <p>God has his Book of Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and whatever you do in time, is there Regiſtred for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <note place="margin">Rev. 20. 12.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>2. As to Death and Judgment.</head>
                  <p>How much it concerns you to be in a daily expectation of, and preparation for them, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, if you conſider,</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>1. As to Death.</head>
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:57120:83"/>
                     <p n="1">1. That Death is certain.</p>
                     <p>All are included in the Statute of Death, (made in <hi>primo Adami)</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 17.</note> no Priviledge can be obtain'd againſt it, nor is there any way to avoid the Sentence of Heaven given for it,</p>
                     <p rend="indent">It is a decree not to be revers'd, <note place="margin">Heb. 9. 27.</note> A Statute not to be repeal'd.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That Death may come ſooner than you are aware of.</p>
                     <p>You ſtand upon dying ground, and know not how ſoon Death's ſithe may cut you down; you are near it in health as well as in ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and in a moment Death may lay his cold hands on your mouth, and ſtop your Breath.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">Since then Death may come in <note place="margin">Job 21. 13</note> a moment, live as expecting it's coming every moment.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That Death when it comes will not ſtay for your Repentance: <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Venientem nemo bil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris mortem recipit, niſi quiſe ad il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam diu compoſueris</hi> Seneca.</note> and if it ſtay never ſo long before it comes, it will come too ſoon if you have not repented.</p>
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:57120:84"/>
                     <p rend="indent">Dye when you live, and you ſhall live when you dye.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>(2.) As to Judgment; <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p n="1">1. That it will be certain.</p>
                     <p>There will be a general, and a particular Judgment; the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, to compleat and perfect the particular, and to manifeſt and declare the Juſtice of it; that, will be at the end of the World; this, at the end of Life; that, at Doomſ-day; this, immediately after the day of Death: It may be a long while before that come, and very likely will, (if the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the <hi>Jews,</hi> a univerſal Promulgation of the Goſpel, a <note place="margin">Quan quam in fine mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di dominus ſemel veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et omnibus, tamen ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulo cuique venit cum adeſt mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis tempus, in dei de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretis nulla litura.</note> Catholick Unity, and Charity among Chriſtians, and the calling in of the Elect, muſt precede it;) but this may come before you think of it, or expect it; it is as ſure as Death, and as uncertain; uncertain (as to the time) to any, and yet moſt certain (ſooner or later) to all; for it is treaſur'd up
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57120:84"/> in God's decrees, and cannot be recall'd.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">He that ſays he comes quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <note place="margin">Act. 17. 31 Rev. 16. 15 3. 11</note> may come ſooner than you think of; <hi>viz.</hi> in his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though not in your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, time.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That it will be impartial. Here, ſome are too great to <note place="margin">1 Cor. 4. 5. Rom. 2. 6 16. Mat. 12. 36. 1 Pet. 1. 17. 2 Cor. 5. 10. Rev. 20. 12.</note> give an account of their Actions to any; but there, both great and ſmall muſt give an account of their Thoughts, Words, and Actions, to God, whether they will or no; here, ſome judge, and others are judged; but there, all ſhall be judg'd: for,</p>
                     <p rend="indent">The Sentence of Death being paſt upon all, Judgment (the conſequent of Death) will paſs upon them too.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That it will (when once paſt) be irrevocable.</p>
                     <p>That ſtate you are found in at Death, will be your everlaſting ſtate; for, Judgment (Death's Second) ſtands at Death's back,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:57120:85"/> and as that leaves you, ſo Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will find you; and as it finds you, ſo it will leave you for ever; for, then your everlaſting ſtate and condition will be actually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and finally ſetled, ſo as never to be alter'd.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">Judgment is the critical time for Damnation and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                     <p>The particular Time when <note place="margin">Matt. 24. 36. 44.</note> Death and Judgment will come is concealed, that none might preſume; but that it will be, is certainly foretold, that none may be ſurprized: and that you may <note place="margin">Latet ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus dies, ut obſerventu omnes.</note> not.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Keep a Regiſter of your Sins; keep your Book, and God will croſs his.</p>
                     <p>Often reckoning makes friends.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Renew Repentance daily.</p>
                     <p>If you would have that day to <note place="margin">Acts 3. 19. Mat. 25. 21 Rev. 7. 17.</note> be a time of refreſhing to you from the preſence of the Lord, you muſt be in ſorrow for your Sins in your day; if then you would
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:57120:85"/> enter into Joy, Sorrow muſt here enter into you; and if then you would have Tears wiped away from your Eyes, they muſt now be found there; for,</p>
                     <p rend="indent">None but Mourners ſhall be <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 4.</note> comforted.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Make the Judge your friend. Chriſt has redeem'd you from ſlavery, that you might be free for his Service; and therefore <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 20.</note> give him that which he has ſo dearly bought, and paid for.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">It will avail you nothing to <note place="margin">Matth. 7. 22. 23. Luke 19. 27.</note> call him Lord then, unleſs you make him your Lord now; for, if here you are not ruled, you ſhall then be deſtroyed by him.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Judge your ſelf.</p>
                     <p>If you judge others, you ſhall <note place="margin">Mat. 7. 1. 2 1 Cor. 11. 31.</note> be brought to divine Judgment; but by judging your ſelf you will prevent it, for, Judgment ſhall not paſs in both Courts; what you condemn, Chriſt will acquit; ſo that if yours be a Court of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:57120:86"/> Judgment, his ſhall be a Court <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 10, 11.</note> of Mercy.</p>
                     <p>Holineſs will give comfort in that day, and a ſerious me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating on it may be a means to promote Holineſs: live there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore well in your day, or blot out the belief of this.</p>
                     <p>If you live to have Children, be careful to bring them up in the <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 4.</note> Nurture and Admonition of the Lord.</p>
                     <p>Some are ſo far from bleſſing God for their Children, that they are ready to ſay (as <hi>Daniel</hi> to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhazzar)</hi> his Gifts be to himſelf, <note place="margin">Dan. 5. 16. 17.</note> and his Rewards to another.</p>
                     <p>Some count them no Bleſſings, or but beggarly ones; and ſome there are, that make them none; for, through their neglect, they prove Curſes inſtead of Bleſſings.</p>
                     <p>They are anxiouſly ſolicitous to get great Eſtates for their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but not at all concern'd, what they are, or ſhould be, to whom they leave thoſe Eſtates;
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:57120:86"/> they are daily contriving for them, how they may live while here, but take no care how they ſhall live, nor where, when they ſhall die, and live here no more: they can tell you when dying, what they ſhall leave for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their Bodies; but nothing of what they did, while living, for the good of their Souls. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Parents! that deſerve to be writ childleſs, and to be raſed out of the number of men: for, <note place="margin">Jer. 22. 30</note>
                     </p>
                     <p rend="indent">If they are worſe than Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels that provide not for the Bodies of their Children, they are as bad as Devils that ſtarve their Souls. <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Make it therefore matter of your great care to promote the Good of their Souls.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>(1.) By endeavouring to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs thoſe evil Inclinations that (by nature) are in them.</item>
                        <item>(2.) By Praying for them.</item>
                        <pb n="152" facs="tcp:57120:87"/>
                        <item>(3.) By being an Example of Good unto them.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="1">1. By endeavouring to ſuppreſs thoſe evil Inclinations, that (by nature) are in them.</p>
                     <p>Folly is bound up in the heart of <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 15.</note> a Child (as Poiſon in a Serpent, and Sap in a Tree) and if care be not taken to ſuppreſs it, it will (like an Impoſthume) break forth when ripen'd by opportunity.</p>
                     <p>Corrupt Nature, is as the Soil; evil Examples, as the Showers; and Temptations as the influence of the Sun; all which help on, and further the Harveſt of Sin, that will quickly come, unleſs timely prevented, and that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be better done, than by plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good Inclinations and Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in them.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">The way to deſtroy Weeds is to ſet good Plants in their room.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. By Praying for them.</p>
                     <p>They are all baſe-born (in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſenſe) untill they are new
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57120:87"/> born; therefore it concerns you to be in travel of Soul for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond birth, that Chriſt may be <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 19.</note> formed in them, and to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſolicitous with God for them, (as <hi>Abraham</hi> for <hi>Iſhmael)</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 17. 18.</note> that they may live, <hi>viz.</hi> live to him here, and eternally with him hereafter.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">
                        <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s Converſion was the fruit of <hi>Monicha</hi>'s Prayer.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. By being an Example of Good unto them.</p>
                     <p>It is true, none are to live by Example, but by Precept; <hi>(Paul</hi> himſelf muſt not be follow'd any farther than as he follows Chriſt) but yet ſince the Example of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents (like the influence of the Moon when joyn'd with a good or bad Planet) does much good or hurt, it concerns them to have a great regard unto it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cato</hi> was more careful of his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour before his Children than before the Senate, and would uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſay, he would be as cautions
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:57120:88"/> of ſpeaking any laſcivious Words before his Son, as he would if he was before a Veſtal Nun; and it muſt be your care to behave your ſelf wiſely before yours: good Advice will make little or no im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion on them, unleſs ſeconded by good Example; and therefore if you would have them walk in a perfect way, you muſt walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them in it.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">Though Children do like <note place="margin">Maxima debetur puero reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia.</note> Children, yet they that are Parents muſt not.</p>
                     <p>There is good reaſon for it, in that,</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>(1.) God commands it.</item>
                        <item>(2.) Equity requires it.</item>
                        <item>(3.) Their Good, and your Happineſs, is concern'd in it.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p n="1">1. God commands it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> commanded that Young-men ſhould be brought up <note place="margin">Dan. 1. 3. 4.</note> for him, Children in whom was no blemiſh: and God (a greater than he) commands, that a Child ſhould be train'd up in the way he <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6.</note>
                        <pb n="155" facs="tcp:57120:88"/> ſhould go. Every one has his way, and every one thinks his way beſt; but it is not ſo; and therefore he muſt be train'd up in the way, not in which he would go, but in <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 2.</note> which he ſhould.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">He that ſays you ſhall not <note place="margin">Exo. 20. 13 Deut. 6. 7.</note> murther, ſays alſo you ſhall inſtruct; and therefore it concerns you to offer them up to God (as <hi>Hannah</hi> did <hi>Samuel)</hi> in their tender <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 24. 28.</note> years.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Equity requires it.</p>
                     <p>They were ſhapen in Iniquity, <note place="margin">Pſ. 51.5. Eph. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> and conceiv'd in Sin, a guilt and defilement they deriv'd from your Loins, which alienated them from the Life of God, before they had of themſelves done either good or evil. Since then you have been the cauſe of ſo much evil to them, it is but juſt to do them all the good you can: by being your Children, they became Children <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 3.</note> of Wrath; and therefore in reaſon and equity, it concerns you to do
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:57120:89"/> what you can to cut off the Entail of Hell, to help them to a happy Being to whom you have given a miſerable one, and to be (ſo far as you can) an inſtrument of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation, as you have been of Generation to them.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">It had been better they had <note place="margin">John 3. 3.</note> never been born, unleſs born again; and that you had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been their earthly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if God be not their heavenly one.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Their Good, and your Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, is concern'd in it.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Their good, <hi>viz.</hi> temporal and ſpiritual, to this Life and a better.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Their temporal good.</p>
                     <p>They that firſt ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note place="margin">Mat. 6 33.</note> of God, and his Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are by Promiſe aſſur'd, that all things needful ſhall be added unto them; and therefore put them early upon it, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour while they are young to make them good, and then they
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:57120:89"/> ſhall be ſure to have whatever is good for them: no good thing ſhall be with-held from them; <note place="margin">Pſal. 25. 12, 13. 34. 9, 10. 84. 11. Prov. 13. 22.</note> their Bread and Water ſhall be ſure, and verily they ſhall be fed, <hi>viz.</hi> as to Neceſſity, if not as to Delight.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">If they are of God's houſhold <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> (the houſhold of Faith) nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you nor they need fear, for, God will provide for his Family.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Their ſpiritual Good.</p>
                     <p>They that are bad when old, were ſo when young: an old Jade was a Colt ill broken, or not well man'd at firſt; and an old Devil <note place="margin">Pſ. 58. 3.</note> was once a young one.</p>
                     <p>And they that are bad while young, are like to be ſo when old; it is not impoſſible they ſhould be good then, (rich Wine <note place="margin">Quis cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtocle.</note> is muddy at firſt) and therefore none ſhould deſpair of them, but very unlikely, and therefore none ſhould preſume upon it; for, as Trees dead in the Spring are ſo in
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:57120:90"/> Autumn, and Bruiſes received in Youth continue in Age, <hi>(Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth</hi> lame by a fall in his <note place="margin">2 Sam 4. 4. 9. 3.</note> Infancy was ever ſo) ſo Sins in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd in Youth are hardly left in Age. But thoſe that are truly good in Youth, will be ſo in Age; a Child train'd up in the way he <note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6</note> ſhould go, will not depart from it when he is old; and therefore it concerns you to put your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into that way while they are ſo.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">That which a Veſſel is ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd with, that it keeps, and that way a Twig is bent, that way it will grow.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Your Happineſs is concern'd in it.</p>
                     <p>Your Children are God's more than yours, his Children commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Ezek. 16. 20. 21. Exod. 2. 9.</note> to your Care, put out to you to be nurſed for him (as <hi>Moſes</hi> was for <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Daughter) and of them you muſt give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count <note place="margin">Ezek. 3. 18, 19.</note> unto him: it is true, if they (when warned by you) turn not
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:57120:90"/> from their Sins, they ſhall dye in them; but if they are not warned by you, their Blood will be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at your hands.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">The <hi>Jews</hi> brought a Curſe upon themſelves and their Poſterity, by crying out, <hi>His Blood be upon us, and our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</hi> and ſo will you upon your ſelf and Children, by your neglect of them.</p>
                     <p>Do you think you ſhall not have Sins enough of your own to anſwer for! that by your Sin bring the Guilt of theirs upon you! Is there no Devil to tempt them to ſin! or do you think he cannot effectually do it, unleſs you aſſiſt him in it? Is it a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to be the child of a Whore, and is it none to be a Child of the <note place="margin">John 8. 44.</note> Devil? Is the Birth of ſuch infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in the eyes of the World! and ſhould not the Life of the other be much more ſo in yours! Is there no hand to murder them but your own! nor any other
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:57120:91"/> way to ſhew your Love to them but by deſtroying them and your ſelf too? Are Harlots condemned by all for deſtroying the Bodies of their Children, and ſhould not thoſe wicked Parents be ſo too who through a neglect of them murder their Souls? Was it an act of Cruelty to drive Children into the Fire and Water (as the <note place="margin">Lev. 18. 21. Ezek. 16. 20, 21.</note> 
                        <hi>Jews</hi> did to <hi>Molech,</hi> and the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then to <hi>Saturn)</hi> and is it none (by ſacrificing them to the Devil) to drive them into Hell! is there no love but in going to Hell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! or will it not be enough that they go thither, unleſs you go too for company! will it be any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to hear them (when there) telling you, what a bloody and cruel Father you was to them, in not ſhewing them the evil of Sin, and the miſery that did attend it? If now you cannot well endure to hear them cry, do but think how much leſs able you will be to hear it in Hell for ever! You may then
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:57120:91"/> (when too late) with a little Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riation complain, and ſpeak truly (what <hi>Lamech</hi> did ſcoffingly) that <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 23, 24.</note> you have ſlain Children to your wounding, and young Children to your hurt; therefore, that you may not, be careful to make your Family as a Nurſery for Heaven, <note place="margin">Pſ. 127. 3.</note> and educate your Children as God's Heritage, that you may ſay <note place="margin">Gen. 33. 5.</note> with comfort at the great day, Lord, here am I, and the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren which thou haſt graciouſly given thy Servant.</p>
                     <p rend="indent">It is one thing to be bleſſed with Children, and another thing to be bleſſed in them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="162" facs="tcp:57120:92"/>
            <head>THE POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>MAny more things I had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd for you; but the Book being already bigger than at firſt I thought it would have been, I ſhall only here give you the Heads of ſome of them.</p>
            <p>Life is the Crown of all earthly Bleſſings, (as Health is the faireſt and brighteſt Jewel upon that Crown) a Bleſſing that none but God can give, <hi>(Pharaoh</hi>'s Magici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans <note place="margin">Ex. 8. 18.</note> could not give Life to a Louſe) a Bleſſing that any thing will be given to ſecure, when in danger <note place="margin">Job 2. 4.</note> of being loſt, (all that a man has will he give for his Life) and that all, both Good and Bad, Rich and Poor, Young and Old, (ſooner
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:57120:92"/> or later) greatly value and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly part with: yet I would not have you (with <hi>Herodotus)</hi> do nothing elſe but attend the Health of your Body, nor be ſo buſie about the good of a natural Life, as to neglect the Concerns of that which is eternal, nor yet to ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glect it, or willingly to do any thing that may deſtroy it; for this would be to ſin againſt your Soul as well as your Body, and to do that <hi>(viz.</hi> to pleaſe the Devil) at your Death, which all wicked Men do in their Lives. Therefore <note place="margin">Phil. 1. 23. <hi>Nec prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vitam, vivendi perdere cauſam.</hi>
               </note> neither on the one hand over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value it, nor on the other hand neglect it, but be thankful for it, and make good uſe of it, and this, by living to the end of living.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Then a temporal Life is well improv'd, when ſpent to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Life that is eternal.</p>
            <p>There is nothing will make you more uſeful while you live, than Learning, <hi>(Paul</hi> was the moſt learned of all the Apoſtles,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:57120:93"/> and God made moſt uſe of him) and there is nothing I deſire more as to this world than that you may attain to an Eminency in it; and that you may, you muſt diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeek after it; for, it will not be got without much labour.</p>
            <p>He that would be a good Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, muſt (as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> ſays) have ſix Properties; He muſt be one of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> good Parts, of a ſtrong Memory, a Mover of Doubts, a Liſtner to the Sayings or Speeches of others, a Delighter in his Studies, and laborious in it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">All excellent things are fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced about with difficulty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> is ſaid to have brought <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trumque jungendo perfeciſſe laudatur.</note> Philoſophy to perfection, by joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contemplative and moral Philoſophy together, (in which <hi>Pythagoras</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> excell'd) and the Philoſopher makes it the moſt neceſſary Head, and firſt Principle of Philoſophy, to know how to uſe Principles; and it will be your Wiſdom, and therefore
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:57120:93"/> ſhould be your Deſign, in all your Studies, to bring them to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, that you may not be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided, as the <hi>Athenians</hi> were by <hi>Anacharſis,</hi> for uſing their money only to count, and their Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge only to know.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Practice will be blind unleſs <note place="margin">Idem eſt non habere &amp; non uti.</note> it ſee with the eyes of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and Knowledge will be uſeleſs, unleſs it walk on the feet of Practice, like his Muſick that was underſtood by none but himſelf.</p>
            <p>Make the Stock Learning, and you may graff what you will up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; but if you will take my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, let it be Divinity.</p>
            <p>When God ſent his Son into the <note place="margin">Luk. 4. 18.</note> World, he ſent him to Preach; and had I never ſo many, I ſhould eſteem it my greateſt Honour, as well as theirs, if they were qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for that Office, truly call'd to it, and faithful in it.</p>
            <p>Two things made Chriſt a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, <note place="margin">Iſa. 61. 1. Joh. 6. 27.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> Unction and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion;
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:57120:94"/> and no leſs makes one now: for,</p>
            <p>None are truly call'd to it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs qualified for it; nor though qualified for it, are any of Chriſt's Miniſters, unleſs authoriz's to it.</p>
            <p>Therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Before you enter upon that Office be qualified for it, and call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it.</p>
            <p>Gifts qualifie for it;</p>
            <p>You cannot teach others unleſs you be firſt taught your ſelf.</p>
            <p>A Call commiſſionates to it;</p>
            <p>Without a Call, you will (like haſty <hi>Ahimaaz)</hi> run without your <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 19, 20. 29.</note> Errand.</p>
            <p n="2">2 When you have entred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Office, be faithful in it.</p>
            <p>Do not enter upon the Office <note place="margin">Sacerdos <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sacerdoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um otium.</note> (as of old the Eccho ſounded) as a Trade to get by, nor through Idleneſs neglect it when you have entred upon it; but out of a Zeal <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 14. 2 Corin. 12. 15.</note> for God, and the Good of Souls, be willing to ſpend, and be ſpent like a Taper that conſumes it
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:57120:94"/> ſelf, by giving Light to others. <note place="margin">A good Miniſter is a Light, and his <hi>Motto</hi> muſt be <hi>Lucendo pereo,</hi> or that of the <hi>Phoenix, Dum pario, pereo. Qui ſibi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, cui bonus!</hi> Heb. 13 4.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">Be a good Miniſter for the good of others, and a good Man for your own.</p>
            <p>Marriage is honourable in all, and Parentage, Parts, and Porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are good Ingredients in a Match, but not the principals to guide your choice; let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your Affections ſo far bribe your Judgment, as to put you upon the choice of a Wife, for Money or Beauty only, but for Religion, the beſt and ſtrongeſt Marriage-knot; ſo ſtrong, that it cannot be cut aſunder; for, they that are thus joyned together, neither Life nor Death can part.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Never pawn your Honeſty to pleaſe your Fancy.</p>
            <p>If you marry, and live to have Children, and have any thing to give them, give them what you can ſpare while you are alive, or at laſt they will thank Death for it, and not you: If you have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to give them, (or whether
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:57120:95"/> you have, or have not) leave them under God's Bleſſing, and you will leave them rich.</p>
            <p>A Table, though never ſo rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> adorn'd, and furniſh'd with Food, differs (according to the <hi>Greek</hi> Proverb) nothing from a Manger: therefore, how meanly ſoever your Table is furniſh'd with Food, let it be furniſh'd with good Diſcourſe, that all that come there, may fare (as of old they did at <hi>Plato</hi>'s Banquets) the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for it afterwards.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The Ear trys Words, as the <note place="margin">Job 12. 11.</note> Mouth taſts Meat.</p>
            <p>In two things the Philoſopher <note place="margin">Pythag.</note> ſays we are like to God; <hi>viz.</hi> in ſpeaking the Truth, and in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing Benefits.</p>
            <p>God is a God of Truth, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye, and they that are like to <note place="margin">Titus 1. 2.</note> him will not.</p>
            <p>God is good, and does good; <note place="margin">Iſa. 63. 8. Pſ. 25. 8. Exo. 34. 6.</note> he is abundant in it; and the more any exceed in Bounty, (which is Goodneſs enlarged)
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:57120:95"/> the more like to him they are.</p>
            <p>Therefore,</p>
            <p>When God enlarges his hand in Bounty to you, do you enlarge yours in Bounty to others. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may begin at home, but it muſt not end there.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Taylor</hi>'s Advice to his Son was, that if God did bleſs him with the things of this World, he ſhould count it his chiefeſt Riches, to be rich in Alms; and it will be your Wiſdom to believe ſo: ſome indeed think it is the next way to be undone; for, what is thus gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, they conclude is thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; but they are miſtaken that think ſo: for it is a way, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſecure what you have, but to encreaſe it, in that, whatever you thus give, you lend, and that not <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 27.</note> to a Bankrupt, but to God, who has all the Riches of Heaven and <note place="margin">Prov. 19. 17.</note> Earth, and ſtands Principal in that Bond which ſecures the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment back again of what you thus lend in this Life, and of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:57120:96"/> better in the Life to come.</p>
            <p rend="indent">I had rather you ſhould want an Eſtate, than a heart to be charitable; a Capacity this way to do good, than a Will or an Inclination to it.</p>
            <p>The holy Scriptures contain'd in the old and new Teſtament, are the Word of God, the Statute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>book <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 16.</note> of Heaven, the Will of your heavenly Father, the Advice of Chriſt your heavenly Phyſician, the Counſel of him your Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 16. Act. 13. 26 Rom 10. 8. 2 Tim. 3. 15. Eph 1. 13.</note> the Word of Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, the Word of Faith and Truth: therefore,</p>
            <p>Believe it firmly;</p>
            <p rend="indent">Here let the Ark of your Faith reſt.</p>
            <p>Read it daily and diligently.</p>
            <p rend="indent">That you may find Chriſt the rich Treaſure in this Field.</p>
            <p>Hear it attentively:</p>
            <p rend="indent">The more heed you give to <note place="margin">Act 16. 14. Heb. 2. 1.</note> what you hear, the more you will remember.</p>
            <pb n="171" facs="tcp:57120:96"/>
            <p>Love it ſincerely:</p>
            <p rend="indent">There is no Love like that to God and his Word; and ſuch as your Love is to his Word, ſuch is your Love to him.</p>
            <p>Meditate on it conſtantly: <note place="margin">Pſal. 1. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">The Bleſſing is entail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them that meditate on it day and night.</p>
            <p>Contend for it earneſtly:</p>
            <p rend="indent">It is the Word of Faith, and <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> you muſt be a Defender of it.</p>
            <p>Obey it faithfully:</p>
            <p rend="indent">You neither read, hear, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, nor believe aright, any more than what you practice.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Action is the beſt part of <note place="margin">Jam. 1. 22, 23.</note> a Chriſtian, and there is no doing, like to that of the Word.</p>
            <p>The Work of Creation being <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Gen. 2. 2. 3. He ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd it, or ſet it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and appointed it to be a holy reſt for his Worſhip.</note> ended on the ſeventh day, God reſted on that day from all his Work which he had made, and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:57120:97"/> bleſſed the ſeventh day, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified it.</p>
            <p>He ſanctified it by Inſtitution, that the <hi>Jews</hi> might ſanctifie it by Obſervation; he, by ſetting it apart to a holy uſe, that they might by keeping it ſo.</p>
            <p>Now as the firſt day on which the work of Creation was finiſh'd was conſecrated, and ſet apart for a holy Sabbath to God; ſo the firſt day on which the work of Redemption was perfected, was ſet apart as a holy reſt unto him: that was (as <hi>Athanaſius</hi> ſays) the end of the firſt Creation, and this the beginning of the ſecond Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation: and as that was kept holy to God, ſo this (as appears by the <note place="margin">Act. 20. 7. 1 Cor. 16. 12. Rev. 1. 10.</note> practice of the Apoſtles, and by the univerſal Practice of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church) has ever ſince for many hundred Years been kept holy to him in the Chriſtian Church, both by converted Jews and gentile Chriſtians.</p>
            <pb n="173" facs="tcp:57120:97"/>
            <p>And I can aſſure you, from my own Obſervation, I never yet knew any, but, the more ſtrict they were in the profeſſion of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the more ſtrict they were in the Obſervation of this day.</p>
            <p>Beſides, there are two reaſons to oblige you to the keeping of this day, that the Jews had not to oblige them to the keeping of their Sabbath; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reſurrection of Chriſt <note place="margin">John 20. Luke 24.</note> from the dead on this day: and, The Deſcenſion of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Since then there are ſuch Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to enforce the practice of it, let it be your great care to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie this day, and that,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ceaſing</p>
            <p>From all evil Works, which are Sins on other days, and double <note place="margin">Sabbatum Satana.</note> Sins on this.</p>
            <p>From all Works of Recreation <note place="margin">Sabbatum Aurei Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuli.</note> or Pleaſure; <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are not natural and neceſſary, but volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and needleſs.</p>
            <pb n="174" facs="tcp:57120:98"/>
            <p>From all Works of Labour, that <note place="margin">Sabbatum Tyri.</note> are not Works of Neceſſity, Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Mercy, nor tending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By doing all the Works of Piety, both publick and private, which are the proper Works of this day; and not barely doing of them, but by doing of them with Exactneſs, Conſtancy, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            <p>The Sacrifices of old were dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Num. 28. 9</note> on the Sabbath-day, and God requires more Service on this day than on others, and an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary exerciſe of Grace in them.</p>
            <p>The whole day is his, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs works of Neceſſity and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <note place="margin">Mat. 127.</note> (relating either to Man or Beaſt) intervene, it muſt be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denoted to him.</p>
            <p>The Duties of the day are not all of a ſort, but various; there are all the means and ways of Communion with God on this day, to take off Tediouſneſs and promote Delight in them.</p>
            <pb n="175" facs="tcp:57120:98"/>
            <p rend="indent">If you come with rejoycing, <note place="margin">Pſ. 122. 1.</note> you will go away ſo.</p>
            <p>Chriſt's coming in the Fleſh was the fulfilling of the Law, the coming down of his Spirit on this day was the fulfilling of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; then he took our Nature; on this, we were made Partakers of his; when he died, he ſhed his Blood effectually for our Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; on this, he ſhed abroad his Spirit abundantly for our San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification; on this day he aroſe, and then his Spirit quicken'd his natural Body; on this day his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit deſcended, and quicken'd his myſtical Body; when he aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he carried our Nature up to Heaven; and on this day he ſent down his Spirit to us. Now my Prayer for you ſhall be,</p>
            <p rend="indent">That the ſame Spirit that deſcended this day may ſanctifie you, that you may ſanctifie this day, and that you by it may be made holy, that you may keep this day holy to God
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:57120:99"/> that made it ſo, that keeping this day of reſt here, you may at laſt be taken up into his Reſt that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains for ever hereafter. <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Live to the Honour of that worthy Name in which you were baptiz'd, and by which you are <note place="margin">Jam. 2. 7.</note> called.</p>
            <p>Baptiſm is a ſacred Flood, ſent, not to drown, but to ſave the World; but then you muſt be in Chriſt, (the Ark) and walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 2. 12.</note> of him, that, as you are in the Bond of the Covenant, you may be alſo under the Bleſſing of it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The outward Baptiſm of Water, will avail you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, <note place="margin">Mat. 3. 11.</note> without the inward Baptiſm of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>The Sacrament of the Lords Supper was inſtituted by Chriſt, and appointed as a ſtanding Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance <note place="margin">Matth.</note> to the end of the World, for the commemoration of Chriſts Death, and his great Love in it, and for the Confirmation of all
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:57120:99"/> thoſe Bleſſings obtain'd by him, to them that believe in him.</p>
            <p rend="indent">They only that are in the Covenant, have a right to the Seal of it.</p>
            <p>Some ſeldom receive it, ſome never, (living in a wilful breach and contempt both of God's Law and Mans) &amp; ſome are careleſs and negligent when they do receive.</p>
            <p>But do you,</p>
            <list>
               <item>(1.) Duely attend upon it.</item>
               <item>(2.) Come worthily to it.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Duely attend upon it.</p>
            <p>While you live in the neglect of it, you reject, not only motives, but inſtituted means, to ſubdue your Corruptions, and ſtrengthen your Graces; queſtion God's Wiſdom, as if he had ordain'd a needleſs and ſuperfluous thing; contemn Chriſt and his Love, as if they were not worth the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, and live in diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a Goſpel Command, and thereby become liable to the Wrath of God.</p>
            <pb n="178" facs="tcp:57120:100"/>
            <p rend="indent">He that came to the Feaſt <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 3. 4, 5, 6, 7, 11, 12, 13.</note> without a wedding-garment was deſtroy'd, and ſo were they too that did not come.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Come worthily to it.</p>
            <p>The Sacrament is a Feaſt, the Souls Exceedings; if you come not to it, you will ſtarve your Soul; if you come unworthily you will poiſon it, eating Damnation as ſurely as you eat Bread, and <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 29.</note> drinking a Cup of Wrath inſtead of a Cup of Bleſſing; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do what you can to come in a worthy manner; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With hungring and thirſting after Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Unleſs you come empty, you <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 6. Luk. 15. 3.</note> wil be ſent away ſo.</p>
            <p>With Faith, without which, <note place="margin">Chriſtus fide digerendus.</note> though you eat, you will never be nouriſh'd.</p>
            <p rend="indent">You may touch the Body, but you will receive no Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue from it.</p>
            <p>With inflamed Love to God for giving Chriſt to you; and to
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:57120:100"/> Chriſt, for offering up himſelf for you.</p>
            <p rend="indent">He is the Founder of the Feaſt, and died to make it.</p>
            <p>With a Heart deeply humbled for Sin, that you may not crucifie him afreſh, but mourn over him, <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 6.</note> who was crucified for you, and by you.</p>
            <p rend="indent">A broken Saviour muſt be received with a broken Heart.</p>
            <p>With Humility, and lowlineſs of mind, as unworthy of the Crums that fall from his Table, much more as a Gueſt to ſit there.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The more humble the more welcome.</p>
            <p>With Praiſe and Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The Feaſt is all of free-coſt, and you can do no leſs than take the Cup of Salvation, <note place="margin">Pſ. 116. 13</note> and bleſs him for it.</p>
            <p>In the Sacrament Chriſt's death is ſhewn forth, and in a holy Converſation his Life; now,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:57120:101"/> when in that you have ſhewn forth his Death, go and ſhew forth his Life in the Holineſs of yours, that it may appear, you have an intereſt in the Power of his Croſs, as well as in the Merit of it.</p>
            <p>Sin is an Impoſtor, it comes of a cheating kind, by the Fathers and Mothers ſide <hi>(viz.</hi> the Devil and your Heart, he is the Incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus and that the Womb.) The firſt Sin (by which you may judge of all the reſt) came into the World by a cheat, and all (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angels or Men) that ever had any thing to do with it, have been deceived by it; your great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 18</note> therefore will be to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the deceitfulneſs of Sin, and <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 13.</note> to watch againſt it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Our firſt Parents expected <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 5, 6, 7.</note> to be as Gods, but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came as Devils.</p>
            <p>Unbelief is a Sin:</p>
            <p>That gave life to the firſt actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Sin, and ever ſince gives life to <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note>
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:57120:101"/> all, and maintains the life of them; in the Judgment, as in a Caſtle; in the Heart, as in a Cloſet; and in the Life, as in a Trade.</p>
            <p rend="indent">All Grace acts in the ſtrength of Faith, and all Sin in the ſtrength of Unbelief.</p>
            <p>A Sin that puts God in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils place, and the Devil in God's: for,</p>
            <p rend="indent">By diſ-believing God, you believe the Devil.</p>
            <p>A Sin that binds the Guilt of all other Sins faſt upon you, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Puniſhment, but this binds you over to it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Hell ſeems to be prepar'd on purpoſe for Unbelievers, and Hypocrites as the chief of Sinners.</p>
            <p>I hope you have ſo much Faith <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 12. <hi>Quantò magis à Deo rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimus, tantò mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſumus.</hi>
               </note> as to believe this, that you may take heed, and beware of an evil Heart of Unbelief, in departing from the living God.</p>
            <p rend="indent">By going from a living God, will go to a killing Devil.</p>
            <pb n="182" facs="tcp:57120:102"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pambo</hi> was thirty years (as he ſays) learning how to rule his Tongue, and yet had not perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learn'd that Leſſon: and Saint <hi>James</hi> tells us, the Tongue is an unruly Member, not eaſily ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; yet an endeavour to do it is not more difficult than neceſſary, for, without it your Religion is <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 8. 1. 26.</note> vain.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The Sins of the Tongue are many; but I ſhall here only adviſe you in an eſpecial manner to beware of three; <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Of Swearing.</item>
               <item>Of Cenſuring.</item>
               <item>Of Lying.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Swearing.</p>
            <p>The Tongue of Man is call'd <note place="margin">Pſ. 57. 8. 108. 1.</note> his Glory, not only as it is one of the Excellencies and Prerogatives of Man over other Creatures, by this to expreſs his mind; but as it is an Inſtrument ordain'd for the ſetting forth of Gods glory. When thus employ'd, it is his Honour;
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:57120:102"/> but when in curſing and ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; it is a Shame and Reproach unto him, and a Diſhonour to God, who has by this put ſuch an Honour upon him above all earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Creatures.</p>
            <p>I hope you will never meet with a Temptation to this Sin, nor much need any caution from me againſt it: but ſince you live in an Age in which this Sin is as common as it is notorious and abominable, you will do well to remember the Threatnings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd by God againſt this Sin, and the Judgments inflicted upon them that have been guilty of it; how vile and contemptible it will make you in the Eyes of all that are ſober and vertuous; that it will by this manifeſtly appear, that you are rotten at the heart; (for out of the abundance of the Heart the Mouth ſpeaks) that <note place="margin">Luk. 6. 45.</note> your Mouth is full of deadly Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (an unlikely place, one would think, to look for Poyſon in) and <note place="margin">Jam. 3. 8.</note>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:57120:103"/> that your Tongue is ſet on fire of Hell, that ſends forth a ſtench worſe than that of the Fire and Brimſtone there, and will at laſt for ever torment you there: for, <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 10.</note> as rich men by frequent ſwearing, may, by the Laws of Man (if due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly executed) ſwear themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Beggery; ſo both Rich and Poor will, by the Law of God, ſwear themſelves into Hell.</p>
            <p>Every Swearer loſes his Soul for nothing: other Sins have ſome Pleaſure or Profit attending them, but this has neither.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Cenſuring.</p>
            <p>Many (as <hi>Seneca</hi> complain'd in his time ſome did) make more uſe of Spectacles than Looking-glaſſes to behold others Faults more than their own. They read men (as they read Books) only to eſpy out their Faults; they feed (like flies) not on their ſound, but ſore part, and make their Sins either matter of their Triumph or Cenſure: but it is great Folly for you (or any)
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:57120:103"/> ſo to do; for, did you but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how liable you are to the ſame, or worſe Temptations, and how much by nature you are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clin'd to yield to them, you would not.</p>
            <p>God's Judgment begins at his own Houſe, but yours muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at your own Heart; there it muſt begin, and there it muſt end too: be not therefore (as the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae)</hi> quick-ſighted abroad to ſee the Faults of others, and blind at home, not to ſee your own; but behold your own more than theirs; or rather, your own, and not theirs; that you may not (with the <hi>Phariſee)</hi> accuſe them, but (with the <hi>Publican)</hi> condemn your ſelf.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The better any are, the leſs ſevere they will be to others, and the more to themſelves. <hi>Matthew</hi> is call'd <hi>Levi</hi> by all the other Evangeliſts; but he calls himſelf, <hi>Matthew</hi> the <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 3.</note> Publican.</p>
            <pb n="186" facs="tcp:57120:104"/>
            <p n="3">3. Lying.</p>
            <p>A Lyer (as one ſays) is one that defies God, and ſhrinks at Man, but hated of both. Therefore,</p>
            <p>Do not lye at any time:</p>
            <p rend="indent">For though Truth is not to be ſpoken at all times, yet there is no time for a Lye.</p>
            <p>Do not lye upon any account:</p>
            <p rend="indent">No not in jeſt; for, (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> ſaid to one lying in jeſt) if you approve and practiſe it in jeſt, you will ſoon find it in earneſt in all your Actions.</p>
            <p>Do not lie for any thing, no not for the greateſt Advantage.</p>
            <p rend="indent">
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> profeſs'd, he would not tell a Lye to gain Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>Do not lye to any one;</p>
            <p rend="indent">No not to the Devil, to whoſe Nature it is moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>Do not lye for any one:</p>
            <p rend="indent">Not for a Friend; for it is <note place="margin">Magis ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca veritas.</note> no true Friendſhip, to be
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:57120:104"/> falſe to the Truth for a Friends ſake.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Not for Truth it ſelf; for Truth can never be upheld with a Lye.</p>
            <p rend="indent">No not for the God of <note place="margin">Job. 13. 7.</note> Truth; for it is a Sin to ſpeak wickedly for God himſelf.</p>
            <p>But ever ſpeak the Truth of <note place="margin">Veritas entis, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> your Mind, though you may not at all times be able to ſpeak to the Truth of Things; that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear you are a Child of God (the <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 4</note> God of Truth) and not of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, who is the Father both of <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 44.</note> Lyes and Lyers.</p>
            <p rend="indent">By Perjury you exceed the Devil, and by lying you imitate him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plato</hi> wrote over his School, <hi>Let none enter in here that is not a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Geometrician;</hi> and Chriſt admits none into his, but ſuch as deny themſelves: a bare Profeſſion of <note place="margin">Matt. 16. 24.</note> Chriſt is not enough, unleſs you follow him; nor following him,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:57120:105"/> unleſs you deny your ſelf for him. If therefore, you either profeſs, or deſire to be a Diſciple of Chriſt, you muſt live in the daily exerciſe of ſelf-denial, <hi>viz.</hi> both of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſinful ſelf; the firſt in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Dependance, the latter in <note place="margin">Philip. 3. 8, 9. Eph. 5. 11.</note> reſpect of Communion; one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratively, the other abſolutely.</p>
            <p rend="indent">If the Foundation be not good, whatever you build upon it will fall to the ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Macrobius</hi> honour'd <hi>Hippocrates</hi> with this Title, <hi>That he could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deceive, nor be deceived;</hi> but you live in an Age, wherein you will find many skilful in the art of Deceiving; and your tender Years, and want of Experience, may not be Armour of Proof againſt their Wiles: therefore, try your ſeeming Friends before you truſt them (as ſome do their Veſſels, firſt with Water, and then with Wine) and never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect much from them, and you
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:57120:105"/> will never be deceived by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trajan</hi> advis'd his Maſter to tell him of his Faults; ſaying, He would not be angry with him for it, but with himſelf for deſerving it. <hi>Alexander</hi> turn'd away a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher for not doing of it, as <note place="margin">Aut errores non intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis, &amp; inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piens, aut ſi intilligis, adulator, quia non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prebendis.</note> one that was either a Knave or a Fool. And if you rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand your ſelf, you will eſteem them as your beſt Friends, that are Enemies to your Vices.</p>
            <p>It is better (according to the <hi>Greek</hi> Proverb) to fall among Crows than Flatterers; for, they will not eat you until you are dead, but theſe will eat you up while you are alive.</p>
            <p>There are but two ways by which you are ever like to hear of your Faults; <hi>viz.</hi> either by the Reproach of a biter Enemy, or the Reproof of a faithful Friend; confute the firſt by your Life, and make him a Lyer; be thankful to the other, and receive it as a kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <pb n="190" facs="tcp:57120:106"/>
            <p rend="indent">A Friend loves at all times, <note place="margin">Pſ. 141. 5. Pro. 17. 17</note> but never more than when reproving.</p>
            <p>When you hear of any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation given you, enquire who they were that prais'd you; if Vertuous, make good their Words; if Vicious, ſuſpect your ſelf.</p>
            <p rend="indent">What Evil have I done, ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> that this bad man commends me?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a Saying, that we muſt fly to Mount <hi>Gerizim,</hi> but creep up to Mount <hi>Ebal;</hi> that is, we muſt be ſwift to Mercy, and ſlow to Anger: and it will be your Wiſdom to do ſo.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Paſſion is a ſhort Madneſs; it may paſs through a wiſe man's Heart, but reſts no where but in a Fool's.</p>
            <p>What is one man's Duty, may be another man's Sin; and what is lawful at one time, may not be <note place="margin">Pr. 26. 4, 5</note> lawful at another; it will be your Wiſdom therefore, to underſtand
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:57120:106"/> your Duty, the proper ſeaſon of it, and to do it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Duty muſt be done, though Safety be hazarded by it.</p>
            <p>Make that out of Queſtion that ought to be matter of the greateſt Queſtion; <hi>viz.</hi> Whether Chriſt <note place="margin">2 Cor. 13. 5.</note> be in you; if Chriſt is not, the Devil is; but if Chriſt is, then <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 1</note> you are a new Creature.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Then Chriſt is formed in you, when you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Image of <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 29</note> him.</p>
            <p>There are ſome that pray, but <note place="margin">Prov. 28. 9</note> turn away their Ear from God's Law; and ſome that never pray (they turn away both Ear and Mouth from God) the firſt are Hypocrites, the latter Atheiſts: <note place="margin">Mat. 23. 14.</note> none are good that do not pray, nor any, that do no more; for, Hypocrites pray, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways: therefore neither neglect <note place="margin">Job 27. 10</note> Prayer, nor truſt in it; be not falſe to your Profeſſion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by living without Prayer, nor
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:57120:107"/> falſe to your Prayers, by living contrary to them; but own that <note place="margin">Domine fac me in iis conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendis o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peram collo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eare, pro quibus ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinendis ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leo ad te orare. <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas More's <hi>Prayer.</hi>
               </note> in your Life that you do in your Prayers; for, Prayer is not only a means to get good, but an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to be ſo.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Daily Prayer is as neceſſary for your Soul, as daily Bread for your Body.</p>
            <p>Some live as if there was no Heaven, and ſome, as if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd no other Heaven but what is here, (no Paradiſe, but an earthly one;) but do you live in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of it, and have your Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation there while you are here, <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 20.</note> that you may be there when you ſhall be here no more.</p>
            <p rend="indent">A heavenly Converſation <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 23 Heb. 12. 14</note> will at laſt bring you to a heavenly Habitation.</p>
            <p>Some believe there is no Hell, ſome think there is none but a guilty Conſcience, (and if it were true, that will be bad enough,) ſome fear no other Hell but Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and ſome will not think
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:57120:107"/> of Hell, leſt melancholy Thoughts ſhould drive them to Deſpair; but do you ever fear Hell, that you may never feel it.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Chriſt's own Diſciples <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 28.</note> were bid to fear Hell, and did good; and bad think more of it; both might be better.</p>
            <p>Do nothing againſt Conſcience truly inlightned. <note place="margin">Quicquid ſit contra conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am aedificat ad geben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam.</note>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot have a better Friend (next God) than Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, nor a better Jury to acquit you; therefore keep that your <note place="margin">Conſcientia eſt animae paedagogus, ante pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum froe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, poſt peccatum flagellum.</note> Friend whoever is your Enemy; Peace there, though you have none any where elſe; if you do not, you may want a Friend when you will moſt need him: for,</p>
            <p rend="indent">At the day of Judgment, when the Mouth of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſhall be open, yours will be ſhut. <note place="margin">Matt. 22. 12.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="194" facs="tcp:57120:108"/>
            <p>You live in a World full of <note place="margin">Job 5. 7.</note> Troubles; and there is but little (if any thing) elſe, that you can be ſure of; it will be your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom therefore to expect them, and prepare for them before they come, and patiently to bear them when they do.</p>
            <p rend="indent">If you fly the Croſs, you may loſe the Crown.</p>
            <p>The things of this World are requiſite, that none ſhould under-value them; but momentary, that none ſhould over-prize them: <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 30, 31.</note> love them therefore as if you did not love them, and live above them while you live in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them.</p>
            <p rend="indent">It is Folly to love any thing much, that you cannot love long.</p>
            <p>Be eſtabliſhed in the Truth, that you may not be blown about with every Wind of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 14.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="195" facs="tcp:57120:108"/>
            <p rend="indent">Diſtraction of Mind is ſad, but Diſtraction of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is worſe.</p>
            <p>Engage not in any thing in which you cannot expect God's Bleſſing; nor ever expect any Bleſſing from him in any thing, in which you are not firſt counſelled by him.</p>
            <p rend="indent">In all your ways acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <note place="margin">Pro. 3. 6.</note> him, and he will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect your Paths.</p>
            <p>Be juſt to all, and deceive none; if you do, you will deceive your ſelf moſt of all.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Honeſty is the beſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy.</p>
            <p>Patiently bear Reproaches. At the day of Judgment there will <note place="margin">Luke 6. 22, 23.</note> be a Reſurrection of Names as well as of Bodies, and then all <note place="margin">Jude 15.</note> things ſhall be ſet right.</p>
            <p>Heartily forgive Injuries; if <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 35.</note> you do not, you will do a greater Injury to your ſelf. It is no Pride to refuſe to act below your ſelf:
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:57120:109"/> you ought therefore to be ſenſible of them, and to make them, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are, ſenſible of their Evil, that have injured you; but you muſt not revenge it: not to be ſenſible, is brutiſh; to revenge is deviliſh.</p>
            <p rend="indent">A wiſe Man will make bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter uſe of his Foes, than a Fool can of his Friends.</p>
            <p>Never forget a Kindneſs you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, nor remember any you have done to another.</p>
            <p rend="indent">The firſt is Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, <note place="margin">Haec benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis inter du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os lex eſt, Alter obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſci debet dati ſtatim, alter accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti nunquam.</note> the latter is a <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Merchandize rather than a Gift.</p>
            <p>Be more afraid to be evil, than to be ſeen to be ſo; and more aſham'd not to do good, than to <note place="margin">Bona agere &amp; mala pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, regium eſt.</note> be reproach'd for doing of it.</p>
            <p>You may deprecate Shame, and complain of it too, <hi>(David</hi> did both;) but you muſt not, either <note place="margin">Pſ 119. 31 Pſ. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 19 20.</note> ſhun, or fly from Duty, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void it.</p>
            <pb n="197" facs="tcp:57120:109"/>
            <p>Live the Life of Faith here, if you would live the Life of Sight hereafter, and evidence your Faith by your Works; for, it is no more, without them, than <note place="margin">Jam. 2 <hi>ult.</hi>
               </note> Fire is without Heat and Light.</p>
            <p rend="indent">They are none of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Children, that do <note place="margin">Job 8. 29.</note> not <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Works.</p>
            <p>Live above the inordinate love of Life, and ſinful fear of Death; and that you may, make all ſure before you die; that when you come to dye, you may have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do, but to dye.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Pulchra res eſt, conſummàſſe vitam ante mortem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> gave it as his chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Inſtruction to his Children, that they ſhould prefer the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God, and his holy Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, above worldly Wealth, yea above the Empire; and it will be your Wiſdom to value it above all the Riches and Honours of this World: certainly there is
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:57120:110"/> great Excellency in Religion, in that, the Enemies of it ſo often put on a form of it, its Friends (notwithſtanding all hazards) ſo much own it, and appear for it, and God (who is glorious in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs) ſo much commends it, and approves of it; let your eſteem therefore be of all Perſons, for the <note place="margin">Tantus quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que eſt, quantus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Deum.</note> Religion you find in them; if God does ſo, well may you do it too.</p>
            <p rend="indent">It is Religion, more than Blood, that ennobles; for, <hi>The Righteous is more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent than his Neighbour;</hi> viz. <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 26</note> indefinitely, whether rich, or poor.</p>
            <p>The Fear of the Lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning <note place="margin">Pſ. 111. 10</note> of Wiſdom, the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all Religion, a good Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor to Devotion, and a great help againſt Formality in it; a <note place="margin">Cuſtos In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiae.</note> Preſerver of Innocency, and an eſpecial Remedy againſt hardneſs of Heart; (Fear, in a natural <note place="margin">Iſa. 60. 5.</note>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:57120:110"/> ſenſe, contracts the Heart; but in a ſpiritual ſenſe, enlarges it) a Grace like the ſenſe of touching, that (as the Philoſopher ſays) is <note place="margin">Ortu primus uſu maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ultimus.</note> firſt in being, of greateſt uſe, and of longeſt continuance.</p>
            <p>Servile Fear ariſes from Hatred to God; filial Fear ariſes from Love to him; they that fear God, and do not love him, hate him <note place="margin">Nemo meli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us diligit quam qui maximè veretur of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere. <hi>Salvian.</hi>
               </note> becauſe they fear him; but the more any love God, the more they reverence and fear him.</p>
            <p>God is to be fear'd, as well as lov'd and prais'd for his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and your Duty is as much <note place="margin">Hoſ. 3. 5.</note> to fear him, as to rejoyce and <note place="margin">Pſ. 76. 11.</note> truſt in him.</p>
            <p>His Mercy is from everlaſting <note place="margin">Pſ. 103. 17.</note> to everlaſting upon them that fear him, and his Curſe againſt them that do not; ſo that if you are above his Fear, you are under his Curſe; and if here you do not tremble before him with an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diential Fear, you ſhall hereafter,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:57120:111"/> to all eternity, with a deviliſh one.</p>
            <p rend="indent">Fear God, and you need not fear any thing but him, and for him.</p>
            <p>Chuſe God for your Portion, and you can never want.</p>
            <p>You are proud, and think too well of your ſelf, if you cannot be content in any condition with him; and of a low and baſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, if you can be ſatisfied with a whole World without him.</p>
            <p rend="indent">More you need not, and leſs will not do.</p>
            <p>Renew your Repentance before him daily, and beg Pardon and Remiſſion of all your Sins, (as to Kind, Degree, and Aggravation) that, as the Morning Cloud, they may ſoon vaniſh &amp; diſappear; beg the powerful Aid and Aſſiſtance of his Grace, which is ſufficient for you, that Bounds may be ſet to the raging Sea of Sin, that it may never overflow your Banks, and a daily encreaſe of Grace from
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:57120:111"/> him (who is the God of all Grace) that your way may be as the Morning-light ſhining more and more unto the perfect day. <note place="margin">Pro. 4. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">You were never good, if you think you are good enough; nor have any Grace, if you think you want none.</p>
            <p>Live up to that Profeſſion you make of God, to that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you have with him, and thoſe Duties you perform to him, that it may appear you have Truth in the inward parts, and are ſound at the root. <note place="margin">Pſ. 51. 6. Deut. 32. 4. Jer. 5. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p rend="indent">He is a God of Truth, and his Eyes are upon the Truth.</p>
            <p>Let a Zeal for his Glory be writ upon your Heart, that you may honour him in all your ways to him, and acknowledge him in all his ways to you both, of Mercy and Judgment, with Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Humility.</p>
            <pb n="202" facs="tcp:57120:112"/>
            <p>Do his Will chearfully, and bear it patiently; bleſs him for what you have, and depend upon him for what you want; live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him as your happineſs, and to him as your end; thus living to him here, you will live for ever with him hereafter.</p>
            <p>This is the Advice of your earthly Father, from his, and your heavenly Father, and if diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerv'd by you, though you may loſe me your earthly Father, you will never be without the teaching Guidance, Counſel, Care, and Bleſſing of God, your heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father.</p>
            <p rend="italic indent">Non eſt orphanus, cui mortuus <note place="margin">Pſ. 27. 10.</note> eſt parens, ſed qui ſcientiam <note place="margin">Arab. Pro.</note> non habet, nec mores.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:57120:112"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>THE three laſt lines in page 38. ſhould have been the three firſt in page 39.</p>
            <p>The two laſt lines in page 39. ſhould have been in a Parentheſis two lines above.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eminenter</hi> in the fourth line of page 59. ſhould have been ſet in the Margin.</p>
            <p>Page 68. line 12. for <hi>connectuntur,</hi> read <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 79. line 2. leave out <hi>And.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
